<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary's choice, or, The choice of the truly godly person opened, and justified, in a sermon preached at the funeral of Mrs. Anne Petter, late wife of the Reverend Mr. John Petter, Pastor of the Church at Hever in Kent, April 26, 1658 by John Glascock ...</title>
            <author>Glascock, John, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12271999</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12271999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58289</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42839)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58289)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 628:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mary's choice, or, The choice of the truly godly person opened, and justified, in a sermon preached at the funeral of Mrs. Anne Petter, late wife of the Reverend Mr. John Petter, Pastor of the Church at Hever in Kent, April 26, 1658 by John Glascock ...</title>
                  <author>Glascock, John, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Samuel Gellibrand ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke X, 42 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58289:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mary's Choice, OR, The CHOICE of the truly Godly Perſon Opened, and Juſtified, IN A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. ANNE PETTER, Late Wife of the Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. JOHN PETTER, Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Hever</hi> in <hi>Kent. April</hi> 26. 1658.</p>
            <p>By JOHN GLASCOCK, Late Fellow of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and now Paſtor of the Church at Little <hi>Canfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 114. 30.</bibl> 
               <p>I have choſen the way of Truth.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 12. 26.</bibl> 
               <p>The right<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous is more excellent then his Neighbour.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 31. 30.</bibl> 
               <p>A woman that feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be praiſcd.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 112. 6.</bibl> 
               <p>The righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Chriſtianus eſt Filius Dei, Haeres Regni, Frater Chriſti, Socius Angelorum, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Mundi, particeps Divinae Naturae.</p> 
               <bibl>Luther.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Utere Caducis Fruere Aeternis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> f<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> at the Golden Ball in Pauls Church-Yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:58289:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58289:2"/>
            <head>Mary's Choice.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LUKE Chap. 10. Verſ. 42.</bibl>
               <q>But one thing is needfull and Mary hath choſen that good part which ſhall not be taken away from her.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words deſervedly challenge our beſt attention, not onely becauſe of the moſt excellent matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them, but alſo in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the moſt incomparable Author, our dear Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom they were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>They may be conſidered two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Relatively:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Abſolutely.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their Relative capacity is that whereby they hold forth upon what terms they ſtand with the Context; as the diſcretive particle [But] which ſtands in the front of the Text, intimates.</p>
            <p n="2">2. According to their Abſolute capacity, they are conſidered
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58289:3"/>
as they lie intirely of themſelves; For brevity ſake I ſhall han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them under this laſt Conſideration.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of the words is, Chriſts weighty commendation of a worthy Woman: Their principall parts are three.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A remarkable Affirmation.</item>
               <item>2. A ſeaſonable Commendation.</item>
               <item>3. An irrefragable Confirmation.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. A remarkable Affirmation. <hi>One thing is needfull.</hi> Chriſt doth not ſpeak here of an ordinary, arbitrary buſineſſe; but of that which is neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſeaſonable Commendation is expreſſed in the next words, <hi>And Mary hath choſen that good part.</hi> We read in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 40. of <hi>Martha</hi>'s complaint of her ſiſter <hi>Mary,</hi> for leaving her to ſerve alone; In <hi>Verſ.</hi> 41. Chriſt ſeemingly, at leaſt, checks <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> for being over ſolicitous about that ſervice of preparing for his bodily repaſt; Which although a very good, and neceſſary work in its kind and order, yet not altogether faultleſſe, when by reaſon of it better ſervice was neglected. And then in the words of the Text, Chriſt in ſtead of checking <hi>Mary,</hi> as her ſiſter <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> by her complaint ſeemed to expect, beſtowes a ſingular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation on her. Where two things are obſervable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A deſcription of the perſon commended, by her Name, <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The matter of her Commendation, <hi>viz.</hi> Her good choice: <hi>Mary hath choſen that good part.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. The irrefragable Confirmation followes in the laſt words. Chriſt doth not barely aſſert, but alſo ſtrongly prove the goodneſſe of her choice by an Argument taken from the duration of the good ſhe choſe; It was moſt durable. <hi>Which ſhall never be taken from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not abuſe your patience by inſiſting upon what <hi>Stella</hi> and other Popiſh Writers, largely comment upon the Text, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the two kindes of lives, Contemplative and Active, which they gather from the different behaviour of theſe two ſiſters, <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Martha;</hi> but ſhall premiſe a brief, and generall received In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Words, among learned and judicious Divines, and then propound out of them the Doctrinall Concluſion, which ſhall ſet bounds to my preſent Diſcourſe, and your Chriſtian at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58289:3"/>
1. <hi>One thing is needfull.]</hi> That is, one kind of Proviſion, ſay ſome, as if Chriſt had ſaid in other words; O <hi>Martha,</hi> thou needſt not be at ſuch coſt, and paines to prepare many, and rare proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to entertaine me with; One diſh of ordinary fare will be more eaſily procured by thee, and better accepted by me. <hi>Damnat Chriſtus, nimias occupationes quibus diſtringebatur Martha in ſeſe excipiendo: Chriſtus enim non eſt delicatus hoſpes, non af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectat exquiſitas menſas, non epulas lautas requirit, tenui vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu eſt contentus; magis quaerit nitorem animi exquiſitam fidem, compoſitos mores, &amp; ſimilia,</hi> Aretius <hi>in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> One thing is needfull.] <hi>That is, Chriſt is neceſſary; So o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> Ille ſolus eſt nobis neceſſarius, caetera quae multa ſunt non ſunt neceſſaria. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Serm. de Verbis Domini, Secundum Lucam.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> One thing is needfull.] <hi>That is, to hear the Word of God, and to labour after eternall Salvation: So a third ſort.</hi> Elegit Maria Verbum Dei audire, &amp; ſaluti operam dare. Hunc verum eſſe arbitror ſenſum. Opponit enim Chriſtus ſtudium Mariae ſtudio Marthae. Maria hoc unum curabat ut Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum audiret, &amp; ab eo ſalutem quaereret; Martha ut Chriſto in omnibus quibus poterat, miniſtraret illud unum eſſe neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um dicit, haec multa non ſunt neceſſaria, &amp;c. <hi>Mald.</hi> in locum.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Mary hath choſen that good part.] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, bonam partem elegit, <hi>ſo</hi> Beza, <hi>Suitable to our Engliſh Tranſlation. And</hi> Ambroſe <hi>who tranſlateth as we do, yet interpreteth the words comparatively.</hi> Verbum agnoſcere majus opus eſſe, quam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrare divina ſententiae authoritate definitur, nec tamen Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha in bono miniſterio reprehenditur, ſed Maria, quod melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem partem elegerit, antefertur. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> Serm. <hi>11.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>118.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſſianus</hi> and <hi>Maldonat,</hi> with ſome others, read the words in the Superlative form. <hi>Optimam partem elegit.</hi> Hath choſen the beſt part; for which they render this reaſon <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is not to be underſtood, as if made onely between what <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> did chooſe; but between what <hi>Mary</hi> choſe, and what <hi>Martha,</hi> or any other perſon in the world could make choiſe of, and therefore the Compariſon lying between many, it ought to be expreſſed by the Superlative degree. <hi>Mihi quidem
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58289:4"/>
non videtur noſter interpres melius compationem,</hi> &amp;c. Mald. <hi>in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, I might draw up a ſhort Paraphraſe of the words, and out of it raiſe many uſefull and doctrinall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions; But I purpoſe to take notice of, and to propound onely one which engroſſeth much of the marrow, and ſubſtance of the Text.</p>
            <p>From the remarkable Commendation of Chriſt (who was beſt able to judge) concerning godly <hi>Mary</hi> her choice, as being fixed upon the moſt durable, and conſequently upon the beſt good: the words without violence will afford us this moſt excellent and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> The choice which the truly godly perſon makes, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably and incomparably the beſt choice which can be made.</p>
            <p>For the more orderly and profitable proſecution of this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, four things are to be endeavoured; ſomething is to be ſpoken by way of</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Explication.</item>
               <item>2. Confirmation.</item>
               <item>3. Vindication.</item>
               <item>4. Application.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the explication, and confirmation of this Doctrine, two things are to be ſhewed:</p>
            <p n="1">1. What the true Chriſtians choice is?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the true Chriſtians choice is unqueſtionably, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably the beſt choice which can be made.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt of theſe, before I propound the deſcription of a Chriſtians choice, it will not be amiſſe to premiſe, that the word <hi>[Election</hi> or <hi>Choice]</hi> may be taken two ways,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Largely.</item>
               <item>2. Strictly.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Largely, for that it comprehends both the acts of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and the will. <hi>Electio eſt</hi> 1. <hi>in ratione ſecundum quam intellectus habet judicare quod alteri eſt proponendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> In voluntate, ſecundum quam voluntas habet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, aut impellere, ſive imperare de proſecutione ejus quod ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatum eſt. <hi>Ca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Strictly, For the Wills act onely about the meanes leading
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58289:4"/>
to ſome deſired end: when many meanes occurring, ſome one of them is preferred before the reſt, this act of the Will, by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, is called Election or Choice. The word is here to be taken in the largeſt ſenſe, as relating to the end, as well as the meanes, and may be thus deſcribed.</p>
            <p>The choice of a true Chriſtian is that, whereby his ſoul, aſſiſted by ſpeciall grace, prefers before all other things whatſoever, Chriſt, with all his ſpirituall bleſſings, which he by his bloud hath purchaſed, and God of his grace in his holy Ordinances diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to his people.</p>
            <p>For the help of the underſtanding, and memory of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt capacity, I ſhall analetically reſolve and explain the ſeverall branches of this deſcription.</p>
            <p>In the deſcription theſe parts are principally obſervable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The principle of this choice.</item>
               <item>2. The Object of this choice.</item>
               <item>3. The formal act of this choice.</item>
               <item>4. The fountain of all that good which is choſen.</item>
               <item>5. The meritorious cauſe of it.</item>
               <item>6. The outward and ordinary meanes of its conveyance.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 The Principle by which any perſon is enabled to make this choice. The choice which the Text, and Doctrine ſpeaks of is ſuch, as onely a true Chriſtian can make. Tis as poſſible for a beaſt to deſire to be a man, or a toad to be an Angel, as for any of the Poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſince the Fall, without ſupernaturall, and <note place="margin">Iter ad gratia<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> eſt per gratia<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Proſper.</hi>
               </note>ſpeciall Grace, rightly to chooſe God, and the things of God. And the true and irrefragable reaſon of it is, becauſe, as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher rightly determines, nothing doth or can act beyond the ſphear of its own activity. Wicked ones chuſe their own wayes not Gods. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66. 3. Yea, <hi>They have choſen their own wayes, and their ſoul delights in their abominations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Object of this choice is expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>Chriſt with all his ſpirituall bleſſings.]</hi> A whoriſh heart can be content with a divided Chriſt, nothing leſſe then an whole Chriſt can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie a ſincere Chriſtian. Here two things are diſtinctly to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Primary Object of this choice. Chriſts perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecondary Object. All his Spirituall bleſſings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſts perſon; Who can by words fully expreſſe what glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58289:5"/>
and ſoul-raviſhing beauty the truly godly perſon doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in the lovely perſon of Jeſus Chriſt. Tis admirable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider throughly the large and patheticall deſcription the Church makes of Jeſus Chriſt, by way of anſwer to a queſtion propounded to her by the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Cant. 5. 9. <hi>What is thy Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved more then another Beloved, O thou faireſt among women! What is thy Beloved more then another, that thou doſt ſo charge us?</hi> Verſ. 10. <hi>My Beloved is white and ruddy,</hi> Theſe two being duely mixed do make the moſt beautifull and orient look, or colour, that any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is capable of, and then it followes <hi>[the chiefeſt among ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,]</hi> and becauſe ſo, he deſerves to have as much love as ten thouſand hearts put into one could hold; and this lively and lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſcription of Chriſt is continued to the end of the Chapter. Verſ. 16. <hi>His mouth is moſt ſweet, i. e.</hi> His word, and promiſes which are as it were the breath of Chriſts mouth. We had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be without fire, water, bread, ſun, air, ſaid a <hi>Dutch</hi> Divine, then want that one ſweet ſentence of our bleſſed Saviour <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden and I will give you reſt.</hi> Yea, <hi>He is altogether lovely, totus, totus deſiderabilis,</hi> wholly amiable, every whit of him to be deſited. But as for wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons their judgement of Chriſt is farre otherwiſe; like whores, they preferre the gifts before the giver; and yet not all but ſome onely of Chriſts gifts are acceptable to wicked ones. Chriſts pardon will do well to deliver them from danger, but Chriſts ſinne-ſubduing grace is as unacceptable to them as Chriſts perſon; But of this more in the next branch of the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. A ſhort diſcourſe of this high, and ſpirituall ſubject, <hi>viz.</hi> The lovelyneſſe of Chriſts perſon amongſt many is a dark and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring buſineſſe. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53. 2. <hi>When we ſhall ſee him,</hi> that is, Chriſt, <hi>there is no beauty that we ſhould deſire him.</hi> This was ſpoken in the perſon of the carnall Jew, who judged of Chriſt according to his outward appearance. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>The natural man receiveth not the things of the ſpirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him, neither can be know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> And who wonders that a blind man is not affected with the moſt beautiful object which is before him when he is not capable of diſcerning it. Deformity, and beauty are both alike to ſuch a perſon; tis ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably in Spirituall Objects.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Secondary Object of the Chriſtians choice is thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58289:5"/>
               <hi>viz. [All Chriſts ſpiritual Bleſſings]</hi> A truly godly perſon doth as truly deſire ſanctifying grace, to make him ſerviceable to Chriſt here, as pardoning grace to render his condition happy here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: <hi>He hath his fruit unto holineſs in this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 22.</note>
               <hi>life, as well as the end everlaſting life.</hi> It were an inexcuſable waſt of time to be large in the further proof of this; I ſhall therefore onely name one Text for its full confirmation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings in heavenly places in Chriſt.</hi> Out of theſe words (to omit many things contained in them) for my preſent purpoſe I ſhall obſerve three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Godly <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks theſe words, not in his own name onely but in the name of all the godly <hi>Epheſians,</hi> becauſe it is not ſaid, <hi>who hath bleſsed</hi> me, but <hi>who hath bleſſed us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He gives thanks, not for ſome onely, but for all ſpirituall bleſſings that were procured for them by Chriſt, for ſo are the words, <hi>who hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings.</hi> Now if <hi>Paul</hi> in his own name, and in the name of all the godly <hi>Epheſians</hi> bleſſe God for all ſpirituall bleſſings, by Chriſt; It follows by undeniable conſequence, that he and they did unfainedly deſire them all, otherwiſe their thankfullneſſe for them had been hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall and abominable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His thankfullneſſe for them was equall, therefore ſuch was his and their deſires for them. But is it ſo with the wicked! Who dare affirme it? while they are wicked, they do not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſire to partake of all ſpirituall bleſſings. A curſed <hi>Balaam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 23. 10.</note>may deſire to die the death of the righteous; but no wicked man alive, while ſuch, can deſire to live the life of the righteous.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They do not deſire it. Hear their own words, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 14. <hi>We will not have this man rule over us.</hi> This was a very plain but yet a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rude and rebellious meſſage, and yet ſuch duſt-heaps are found in every corner, ſuch maſterleſſe monſters riſe every where; So that by their own confeſſion, they may be judged and condemned, for being unwilling to live as the holy ſubjects of the King of Saints in this life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They cannot deſire it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 7. <hi>The carnall mind is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt God, for it is not ſubject to the law of God, neither-indeed can be.</hi> By theſe words we ſee plainly, the beſt of an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſon is not onely averſe, but utterly adverſe to the rule of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58289:6"/>
holineſſe, and the Will being guided by the Underſtanding; If <hi>the carnall mind</hi> (as the Apoſtle here plainly aſſerteth) be <hi>enmity againſt the law of God,</hi> the rule of holineſſe, the carnall will cannot poſſibly be for conformity to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Meritorious cauſe of all the good which the truly godly perſon chuſeth, is the precious bloud of the Sonne of God, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <note place="margin">Cauſa proca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactica.</note>graces, and comforts here, and the eternall glory of the other world, are no cheap things, but moſt coſtly, and accordingly ought to be valued, and improved by us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>In whom we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption through his bloud, the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, according to the riches of his grace.</hi> Redemption is a very comprehenſive word, and many times is put for all the benefits of the Covenant of Grace. So that every godly perſon may write this ſuperſcription upon his pardon, aſſurance, perſeverance, and all the other bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits he partakes of by Chriſt in this life. Theſe are the price of bloud, and that the beſt bloud, called <hi>precious,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18, 19. and that worthily, becauſe <hi>the bloud of God, Act.</hi> 20. 28. And ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bloud of an infinite perſon, and conſequently the price an infinite price. This will much more hold true concerning the glory of the other world. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 19. <hi>Having therefore brethren boldneſſe to enter into the holieſt by the bloud of Jeſus.</hi> No getting to the ſhore of glory, but by a ſinners ſwimming upon the moſt precious ſtream of a Saviours bloud. Theſe things ought to be frequently the meditations of Chriſtians to inflame their loves to a moſt lovely and loving Saviour, and to quicken them to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſuitable praiſes for all their coſtly priviledges in both worlds.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 4. The Formall Act of this Choice, is that, whereby they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre Chriſt, and all his ſpiritual bleſſings, before all worldly things whatever. This is the inſeparable property of all, and onely truly godly perſons. That they eſteem God and the things of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other things, is evident in the example of godly <hi>David,</hi> as appeares by thoſe remarkable words recorded in the 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30. <hi>I have choſen the way of truth,</hi> and Verſ. 173. <hi>I have choſen thy precepts,</hi> compared with <hi>Verſ.</hi> 167. <hi>My ſoul hath kept thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> and <hi>I love them exceedingly,</hi> farre more then any thing in the whole world. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 103. <hi>How ſweet are thy words unto my taſte!</hi> yea, <hi>ſweeter then hony to my mouth.</hi> And Verſ. 72. <hi>The law of thy mouth is better to me, then thouſands of gold and ſilver.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58289:6"/>
Thoſe words of the 4. <hi>Pſal. v.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>Many there be that ſay, who will ſhew us any good?</hi> The <hi>(many)</hi> in the Text are all the ungodly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The good was temporall, as is clear from the ſeventh <hi>Verſe.</hi> But now godly <hi>David</hi> prayes for the <hi>light of Gods countenance, i. e.</hi> the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his favour to his ſoul, and profeſſeth that ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious mercy being obtained, would make him <hi>more glad</hi> then any worldling could poſſibly be, <hi>when his corn and wine encreaſed.</hi> Yea, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63. 3. He preferres Gods <hi>loving kindneſſe before life it ſelfe;</hi> And that (as Satan truly) is to be preferred before all other worldly things whatſoever. <hi>Job.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Skin for skin and all that a man hath will he give for his life:</hi> But no wicked perſon living doth ſet ſuch an high value upon God, and the things of God: But if God be twelve with him, ſome worldly Object, to which he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately affected is alwaies thirteen; as appears by thoſe words, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 14. when Chriſt was ſpeaking of the priviledge of the righteous at the reſurrection, one that hears him, cries out, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he that ſhall eat bread in the kingdom of God,</hi> as if he had ſaid in other words, that is a glorious and happy eſtate, I chooſe that for my portion. Chriſt preſently, to diſcover his hypocriſie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds the parable of the gueſts, who were invited to partake of that priviledge he ſeemed ſo much to admire, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17. and then we read <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>they all with one conſent made excuſes:</hi> They ſeemed much to eſteem the priviledge of Chriſtians at the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, but their Oxen, Farmes, Wives, lay much nearer to their heares, for which we read <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>That the Maſter of the houſe was very angry,</hi> as he had great cauſe, as ſhall be hereafter proved.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Cauſa pro<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena.</note> 5. The Fountain of all the good the godly perſon chooſeth is the Free Grace and favour of God towards his precious people; which they all do deſervedly admire in this life, and will upon further grounds more perfectly admire to all eternity in the life to come. The ſhoutings of all the godly in both worlds are, and ought to be Grace, Grace. Tis not conſiderable what carnall Sophiſters may object againſt this truth, becauſe it was aſſerted in the third branch of the deſcription, That all the godly perſons priviledges in both worlds, were dearly purchaſed for them by the moſt precious bloud of Chriſt, the Son of God, and thereupon as they conceive Gods conferring thoſe priviledges upon the Elect, ſeems rather, if not onely, an Act of Juſtice and not at all of Grace.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58289:7"/>
In this haſt, I ſhall ſay no more (and I think more need not be ſaid) then to name that pregnant Text of the Apoſtle for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of that carnall cavil, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>In whom we have redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption through his bloud, the forgiveneſſe of ſins, according to the riches of his grace.</hi> According to bleſſed <hi>Pauls</hi> divinity, Chriſts bloud as the meritorious cauſe of Redemption and Remiſſion, is very well conſiſtent with the grace, yea, the riches of the grace of God the Father. Tis very true, they were exceedingly coſtly to Chriſt, we are the greater debtours to his love for being willing by ſo great a price to purchaſe our peace, tis as true, they are not coſtly to us, we have them <hi>without money and without price,</hi> Eſa. 55. verſ. 1, 2.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The outward and ordinary meanes of conveying of all Chriſts ſpirituall bleſſings into the hearts of Gods people is, the right uſe of his holy Ordinances. The Ordinances of God are <hi>canales gratiae,</hi> the golden pipes by which the golden oyle of grace empties it ſelf into the hearts of Gods people. Tis true, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſad to conſider that many ſlight the Ordinances of Grace, and not onely ſo, but diſcourage others from waiting upon them by ſpeaking according to the language of proud <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Ye are idle, ye are idle, therefore ye ſay, let us go,</hi> let us go, <hi>and do ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the Lord;</hi> So they ſay, becauſe the people of God are idle and unwilling to take paines in their callings, they ſpend ſo much time more then others in gadding to hear ſermons: But alas, though it be eaſie to hear ſermons, as they uſe to do, yet as God requires, and his people endeavour to do, with prepared and fixed hearts, is much harder <hi>to do,</hi> then any exerciſe they were ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with. <hi>But Wiſdome is juſtified of her Children,</hi> Mat. 11. 19. Holy <hi>David</hi> had better thoughts of Gods Ordinances, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 1. <hi>How amiable are thy tabernacles O Lord of hoſts! my ſoul long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yed even fainteth for the Courts of the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. He ſeemeth to envy the Sparrowes that had liberty to build their neſts near Gods Altars. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. he addeth, <hi>One day in thy Courts is better then a thouſand elſe where.</hi> If any demand why <hi>David</hi> is ſuch an admirer and extoller of Gods Ordinances, he gives a ſatisfying account <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>The Lord will give grace and glory.</hi> Grace, and the firſt fruits of glory, are wrought, preſerved, and encreaſed in the hearts of Gods holy ones, in the right uſe of Gods Ordinances. Thus much ſhall ſerve for the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58289:7"/>
               <hi>I come now to the ſecond thing,</hi> That the truly godly perſons choice is unqueſtionably, and incomparably the beſt choice which can be made!</p>
            <p>I ſhall endeavour to make good this concluſion. One would think that amongſt a people profeſſing Religion, and ſo well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed as we in <hi>England</hi> have been for above fourſcore years, a ſhort proof might ſeem ſufficient for this purpoſe; For my part if there were not a line in the Bible to prove it beſides the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. I could not but judge that abundantly convincing. <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle there) <hi>is profitable for all things, having the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> This is truly aſſerted of that which the godly man chooſeth, but cannot be truly ſaid of any thing in the whole world beſides. But becauſe the practiſe of moſt doth plainly declare, that they are not of a right belief in this weighty point, I ſhall further confirm the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the godly perſons choice above all other choices that are or can be made by any ungodly perſon in the world, by one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable Demonſtration, which is as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>That good which the godly perſon chooſeth is the beſt, in order to all the Concernments af this life, and that which is to come.</hi> When this is made good, more need not be ſpoken for the proof of the godly perſons choice, as the beſt choice which can poſſibly be made. For all the concernments of all perſons in the world are reducible to theſe two heads, and therefore that choice which is the beſt in Order to both theſe, is unqueſtionably and incomparably without all diſpute, the beſt choice that can be made.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now addreſſe my ſelf to hold forth the ſeverall branches of this Demonſtration, in that order in which I have propounded them, with their ſeverall proofs.</p>
            <p>The Concernments of this Life are,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Temporall.</item>
               <item>2. Spirituall.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 The godly perſons Choice is the beſt choice which can be made, upon a Temporall account, in reference to the outward good things of this Life.</p>
            <p>Here two things are diſtinctly to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The godly mans Perſonall,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> His Relative Capacity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> As to the godly man, conſidered in reſpect of his Perſon,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58289:8"/>
his choice appeares to be better in reference to temporall good things, then the choice of any ungodly perſon in the world. The wicked chooſeth creature comforts onely, and looketh no further, whether Gods bleſſing, or curſe, go along with them: but the truly godly perſon cannot be content with creature comforts, in the greateſt abundance, if he cannot enjoy God with them. The wicked careth not what courſe he takes to get them, right, or wrong, much at one to him, but the godly perſon ſeeks them onely in a way of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>There are theſe remarkable differences between the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of godly and ungodly perſons, in reference to temporall good things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In point of ſecurity, for the enjoyment of ſuch a meaſure of worldly eſtate as ſhall be neceſſary for them. The wicked perſon hath no ſufficient ſecurity in this caſe. Tis poſſible he may vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boaſt of his <hi>Michaelmas</hi> hundreds or thouſands; But alas, who knows not but that through his own prodigality, the violence and injuſtice of others, and many other wayes, God by his Providence, may order things ſo, that he and his may be reduced to extream wants before his death. What age of the world abounds not with ſad inſtances in this kind! <hi>Belleſarius,</hi> that ſometimes was very rich, before his death begg'd for an half penny. The Apoſtle calls <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 17.</note>them <hi>uncertain riches,</hi> and well he may, for we can have no more hold of them, then of a flock of birds that ſit in a mans yard, which are preſently upon the wing, and are gone. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 5. <hi>Riches certainly make themſelves wings, they fly away as an eagle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven.</hi> Oh that the greedy <hi>Mammoniſts</hi> would ſeriouſly and frequently conſider this heart-weaning conſideration. But all the precious people of God who have made the choice the Text ſpeaks of, have Gods infallible promiſe, which is the beſt ſecurity that can be deſired, that <hi>they ſhall never want any thing that is good for them</hi> (the God of heaven, their moſt wiſe, and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father being Judge) while they continue in this world. This comfortable truth may be proved by many Scripture Arguments; but thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 10. ſeem ſufficient, <hi>They that ſeek the Lord,</hi> as all do that rightly chuſe him, <hi>ſhall not want any good thing.</hi> Upon ſuch a ground as this word of Promiſe <hi>David</hi> did, and every true Chriſtian may, confidently expect at Gods hands, what they ſhall need at any time. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. 1. <hi>The
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58289:8"/>
Lord is my ſhepherd, I ſhall not want:</hi> The true Chriſtian who is in a poor and mean condition in the world, if he be aſſured that he hath made this choice I am now ſpeaking of, may poſſibly live to ſee his purſe often empty, and his cupboard too, but being under a full promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 10. he may anſwer his own ſoul, when tempted by Satan to diſtruſt Gods ſeaſonable proviſion, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did his Son in another caſe, <hi>O my ſon God will provide,</hi> Cen. 22. 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The godly man hath the beſt Right to his temporall eſtate. The wicked have onely a providentiall right as creatures, as hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall <note place="margin">Jus ſoli, non jus coeli.</note>
               <hi>Ananias</hi> had to his eſtate before the ſale of it, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 4. But the godly perſon hath a ſpirituall right to his eſtate as a new Creature, by virtue of his Covenant intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted heir of all things, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 1. 2. This great comfort the Apoſtle mindes the godly <hi>Corinthians</hi> of, and under their name all the godly perſons in the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21, 22, 23. <hi>All things are yours, whether Paul or Apollo, &amp;c. all are yours, and ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods. q. d.</hi> Ye hold all in <hi>Capite tenui,</hi> which is the Beſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſhall have more comfort in his temporall eſtate, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſmall, then the richeſt reprobate in the world can have in his greateſt abundance. Amongſt many other arguments that might be uſed to prove this aſſertion which is ſo great a Paradoxe to the whole company of unregenerate perſons, this is ſufficient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That God ſo faſhioneth the hearts of all his precious people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he maketh them in ſome meaſure to be really contented with that proportion of temporall eſtate which his wiſe and fatherly Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence carves out unto them; but no ſuch comfortable thing is to be found in the heart of the richeſt Chriſtleſſe perſon in the world, notwithſtanding his great earthly treaſures. The ſtrength of this reaſon depends upon making good two Concluſions, which I ſhall diſtinctly propound and prove in their order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion</hi> 1. God makes his people contented with that meaſure of outward eſtate which he thinks fit to beſtow upon them, be it never ſo little. This appears by thoſe excellent words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 11. <hi>I have learned in whatever ſtate I am therewith to be content; I know how to be abaſed, and how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If any ſhould carnally cavil, and ſay, tis true, it was ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58289:9"/>
with <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a <hi>None<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſuch</hi> for eminence of Grace, but it doth not follow, tis ſo with every ordinary godly perſon. One ſwallow makes not a ſummer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solution,</hi> I anſwer, That although in this ſtate of imperfection, neither knowledge, faith, contentment, nor any other ſanctifying grace is perfect in degrees, while we are in this world, but there <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 9.</note>are and will be ſome pangs of unbeliefe, and diſcontent in the moſt precious Chriſtians; Yet where true godlineſſe hath once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Throne, All, even the weakeſt of Gods people are really contented with their worldly condition, and with the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of Gods Providence towards them. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with contentment is great gaine,</hi> that is, with a mind that hath <note place="margin">Dutch Annot.</note>enough, and is content with that which the Lord affords him; which contentment it ſelf alſo ſprings out of godlineſſe; For he that hath Chriſt hath all things with him: So that where true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe enters the ſoul, contentment is alwaies one part of the train, which cannot be ſeparated from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion</hi> 2. No wicked rich man in the world is, or can be contented with his worldly condition, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. The Pſalmiſt ſpeaking of the wicked, ſaith, <hi>their eyes ſtand out with fatneſse, they have more then heart could wiſh.</hi> The learned <hi>Diodate</hi> expreſſeth his thoughts thus upon theſe words; Every thing went on proſperouſly with them, even beyond their own hope, conceit, or deſire: Now, one would think, if ever, they will be content with their worldly eſtate; But alas, no ſuch ſweet flower of true content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ever grew in the barren wilderneſſe of corrupt nature: This is to be found onely in the garden of grace, or paradiſe of glory. For if you look into the next words, you ſhall ſee a true Character of their baſe, curſed, and moſt unworthy diſpoſition, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>They are corrupt, and ſpeak wickedly concerning oppreſſion,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuppoſed to poſſeſſe more then heart could wiſh, yet ſtill greedy of the gain of oppreſſion, their language is like the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaches <note place="margin">Prov. 30. 15.</note>daughters, <hi>Give, give.</hi> Tis poſſible ſome of them obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving how many of the Lords dear people live chearfully, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly with much leſſe then the twentieth part of that they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, may endeavour to avoid ſhame and cenſure amongſt men, to hide their diſcontent, and make a lying profeſſion of being very well ſatisfied with their worldly lot, but (without the leaſt breach <note place="margin">Gen. 33. 9.</note>of charity) I may, and muſt take leave not to believe them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58289:9"/>
their frequent, and confident profeſſions, becauſe it is written <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>He that loveth ſilver ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver, nor he that loveth abundance, with increaſe; this alſo is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> If God ſaith, as it is here expreſſed, that <hi>he that loveth ſilver,</hi> to wit, inordinately (as all wicked lovers of it do) <hi>ſhall not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with ſilver, and increaſe,</hi> I may then ſay to ſuch pretenders to contentment with their worldly eſtates, in point of our faith, as <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles to the Council, as to their obedience; We ought to believe God rather then men. Tis as <note place="margin">Act. 5. 19.</note>poſſible for a wicked man to fill his body with Aire, and his cheſt with grace, as his minde with wealth. Tis with them as with a ſhip, It may be overladen with ſilver, and gold, even unto ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet have compaſſe and ſides to hold ten times more. So here, a covetous wretch, though he have enough to ſink him, yet he ſhall never have enough to ſatisfie him. So that the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which the Pſalmiſt delivers, is moſt worthy to be obſerved, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 16. <hi>A little that the righteous hath is better then the riches of many wicked:</hi> He doth not ſay of how many, becauſe let us think of never ſo many, yea of all of them, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous mans little is better in very many remarkable reſpects then all their greateſt treaſures heaped together: The King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> although the greateſt Prince in Chriſtendome by farre, having his Empire ſo farre extended that he may truly ſay, that the ſun ever ſhines upon his Dominions, yet gives this for his Motto, <hi>Totus non ſufficit Orbis,</hi> The whole world is not ſufficient. God by <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that <hi>in the houſe of the righteous is much treaſure,</hi> Prov. 15. 6. although many times there is ſcarce a good bed to lye, or a ſeat to ſit on. The time will certainly come, when the richeſt wicked men that ever lived will ſee clearly that their account would have been much narrower, and conſequently their condition to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity leſſe miſerable, if they had been ſo poor as to have begg'd their bread from door to door all their lives long. Tis with the bleſſings of this life, as tis with perfumed gloves, when they are richly perfumed, their perfume is much more valuable then the leather, wherof they are made; So not ſo much earthly bleſſings conſidered in themſelves, as their being perfumed with the ſweet love of God in Chriſt, is that which maketh them bleſſings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, truly deſerving the name they bear. Now all the bleſſings of thoſe who have made the choice in the Text, are all thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58289:10"/>
All the barley bread they eat, beit never ſo courſe, all the clothes they wear, be they never ſo mean, with all their other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings, they proceed from the ſame ſweet love of God, wherewith he was moved to beſtow Jeſus Chriſt upon them for ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 32. <hi>He that ſpared not his own ſon, but hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him freely give us all things!</hi> Nothing is more ordinary then for wicked rich men to judge themſelves the onely happy perſons in the world, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 15. <hi>The rich mans wealth is his ſtrong city;</hi> There he is very ſafe, and happy in his own conceit: But as for the poor, in his wicked rich neighbours eye he is deſpiſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 20. <hi>The poor is hated even of his own neighbour: but the rich hath many friends.</hi> But did they conſider that which the Scripture ſpeaks of their condition, they would diſcern no ſuch cauſe to boaſt of it, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 2. God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to <hi>curſe their bleſſings,</hi> (and who is able to conceive how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods curſe is) and not ſome of them onely, but all of them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. from 15, to 22. Conſider O wicked man and tremble to think, the curſe of God fills all thy ſweet cups, and diſhes with wormwood and gall. Gods curſe (as a fury) haunts thee in all thy wayes. In the City it attends thee, in the Countrey it hovers over thee, coming in it accompanies thee, going forth it follows thee, and in travel is thy companion: So that upon the matter, ſo many bleſſings ſo many curſes, the more bleſſings the more curſes. Me thinks I hear all the Lords people bleſſing God for denying them ſuch a miſerable portion. Tis not the great Cage that makes the Bird ſing ſweetly: So tis not the great eſtate that brings with it cordiall contentment. Experience tells us in the ſmall thatch't cottages, where the people of God dwell, are found more chearfull perſons, then in all the ſtately Pallaces of the world, that are poſſeſſed by graceleſſe ones.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us a little conſider the godly mans Relative Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, and there it will be as true, that his Godlineſſe is more for the advantage of his poſterity, then all the gold, and ſilver that are horded up by Chriſtleſſe perſons can be for the benefit of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, except God incline them to chooſe his ways, and then the property of their eſtates is altered, but this is no thank to their Parents.</p>
            <p>Here two things are to be diſtinctly propounded and confirmed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Perſonall goodneſſe is very profitable for poſterity, <hi>Exod.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58289:10"/>
20. 6. God promiſeth to <hi>ſhew mercy to thouſands of them that love</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 112. 1, 2.</note>
               <hi>him and keep his commandements,</hi> Pſal. 37. 22. God promiſeth that the ſeed of his people ſhall inherit the earth. The child of ſuch a Tenant as paid his Rent well ſhall not be put out of his Farm.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The greateſt treaſures that are heaped up by wicked parents for wicked Children are very unprofitable for them. Many a time they are not a quarter ſo long in ſpending, as they were in <note place="margin">Eccl. 5. 14.</note>getting. <hi>De male quaeſitis vix gaudet tertius haeres.</hi> The third heir ſeldom rejoyceth in ill gotten goods; And this is enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the common proverb, <hi>Happy is that ſon whoſe father goes to the Devil.</hi> But ſuppoſe the beſt that can be ſuppoſed in this caſe, that they continue with him; Conſider <hi>Solomons</hi> words, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>There is a ſore evil which I have ſeen under the ſun, namely rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es kept for the owners thereof to their hurt.</hi> Worldlings ſit and brood upon their wealth, and hatch to their hurt; as the ſilly bird doth on the eggs of the Cockatrice. A wicked rich Son is but like a fatted Oxe, fitted for the ſlaughter. The ſunſhine of proſperity ripens his ſin apace. <hi>Bernard</hi> calls ſuch a condition, <hi>Miſericordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am omni indignatione crudeliorem,</hi> A moſt cruel mercy. What good is there in having a rich ſuit with the plague in it, and ſo propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably, a great eſtate with the curſe of God cleaving to every penny of it. Theſe things premiſed, I appeal to all ſober minded perſons to make judgement, whoſe condition is moſt comfortable of two perſons; the one of them who can only ſay, I had a Father, Grandfather, or great Grandfather (judged by the world for wiſe) <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. 7. 3.</note>who to leave me rich &amp; honourable, did riſe early, go to bed late, and all his life long did wickedly with both hands, and when he had climbed as high as he could, and ſcraped as much wealth, as he was in a capacity to get, I not being religiouſly inſtructed, but ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be as vile as I would be, longed for his death, that I might enjoy the honour and eſtate, for which he expoſed his ſoul to the devil by wicked getting, and I am like to drive the ſame courſe by wicked uſing them. Who trembles not to think what a ſad meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 32.</note>ſuch a parent and child will have at the day of judgement, how dreadfully to all eternity they will curſe each other. The other <note place="margin">Eſa. 8. 21.</note>hath this to ſay; Tis true my Parents were of low birth, and mean eſtate in the world, but they were ſuch as loved the Lord Jeſus, and his dear people unfaignedly, brought me up in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58289:11"/>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Exod. 20. 6.</note> and admonition of the Lord, and ſo left me, although mean in the world; yet under very many and exceeding precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, more worth then the whole world, or ten thouſand worlds, <note place="margin">Pſ. 37. 22.</note>if there were ſo many: Who can conceive and expreſſe how joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſuch a Parent and Child will meet together at the laſt day, and bleſſe God, with and for each other, to all eternity.</p>
            <p>We have diſpatched the firſt branch of the Demonſtration, which although it be leaſt conſiderable, yet it was requiſite to be the more largely proved, becauſe moſt doubted of; For <hi>Balaam,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 23. 20.</note>and ſo other wicked men, that like not the condition of Gods people in this world, yet ſeem at leaſt to deſire the death of the righteous, and conſequently their everlaſting ſafety in the other world: We promiſe (and ſhall perform) greater brevity as to the other two branches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The truly godly perſons Choice is unqueſtionably beſt, upon a Spirituall account. I might eaſily be large, but muſt be ſhort in the confirmation of this Concluſion, and that under theſe two heads.</p>
            <p>Their condition ſpiritually conſidered is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Moſt honourable.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Moſt comfortable.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Honour of a godly perſons condition may be eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (to omit other ways) by the light of theſe three Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>They are moſt honourable in
<list>
                  <item>1. Their Relations.</item>
                  <item>2. Their Service.</item>
                  <item>3. Their Guard.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As to the honourable Relations of godly perſons, I ſhall onely name two.</p>
            <p>They are
<list>
                  <item>I. Sonnes of him who is the God of Glory.</item>
                  <item>II. Spouſes of Chriſt, who is the King of Glory.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. All godly perſons are the Children of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26. <hi>For ye are all the children of God by faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> What great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er honour can be deſired then for God to ſay to poor duſt as it is written, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 18. <hi>I will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters. Jacob</hi> was at great paines and patience to <note place="margin">Gen. 29. 18, 25, 27, 28.</note>become ſon in Law to churliſh <hi>Laban:</hi> and <hi>David</hi> held it a great honour to be ſon in law to King <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 23. and <hi>v.</hi> 27.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58289:11"/>
we ſee with what difficulties he encountred to climb to that height of honour; But alas, that was nothing to this, , the Honour of this is not to be ſpoken, or thought of, without the higheſt admiration, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Behold what manner of love the father hath beſtowed on us, that we ſhould be called the ſons of God.</hi> That note of admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Behold,</hi> could never be more fitly uſed, then in a diſcourſe upon ſuch an honourable priviledge as this of Adoption. A true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may confidently call him Father, who is the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; Chriſt bids <hi>Mary</hi> tell his Brethren (and what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">John 20. 17.</note>news could be told) that when he aſcended, it was to their Father, as well as his Father, their God as well as his God; And tis conſiderable, that this honourable priviledge of Adoption is equally conferred on all true believers, how weak ſoever they are <note place="margin">Credo fide lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guida ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men fide, <hi>Dr. Cruciger.</hi>
               </note>in the Faith of Chriſt. The leaſt bud draws ſap from the root as well as the greateſt branch; The weakeſt hand may as truly receive a ring of gold, and be enriched by it, as the ſtrongeſt hand that is; A weak faith is a joint poſſeſſour, although no faith can be a joint purchaſer of this glorious priviledge. The infant new born is as truly and as much a Child as the eldeſt child in the family. Now although many that never made this Choice I am now ſpeaking of, will frequently with abhorred impudency call God Father, yet all their Rhetorick will not prevail with God to ſpeak to them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that language he uſeth to his own, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 18. <hi>I will be your Father, and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters.</hi> Certainly this impudency of theirs in calling God father, is greater then they are aware of; If a perſon of quality, and approved piety, ſhould paſſe through a town, and ſome ragged beggar, the known child of ſome notorious ſtrumpet ſhould run after him, and preſume to call him Father, what an high diſgrace and hatefull affront would this be judged to be by all ſober perſons! Tis far worſe when a wicked man preſumes to own God under this title. We may in part perceive with what indignation ſuch wicked ones will be rejected by God, by thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 8. 44. in <hi>verſ.</hi> 41. of that <hi>Chapter</hi> the wicked <hi>Jews</hi> laid claim to God as their Father: <hi>We have one father, even God.</hi> But Chriſt could not brook that Satans brats ſhould diſgrace his Father by uſing ſuch language, and therefore in <hi>verſ.</hi> 44. he tells them plainly, they were <hi>of their Father the devil,</hi> his holy Father ſcorned ſuch unholy Sonnes, and he an holy Sonne was aſhamed to be a brother to <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58289:12"/>
ſuch unſanctified perſons; <hi>Such honour have onely the ſaints.</hi> Pſal. 148.</p>
            <p n="2">II. All true believers who have made the holy Choice I am ſpeaking of, are the honourable Spouſes of Jeſus Chriſt, the King of Glory. So the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the believing <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>I have eſpouſed you to one husband, that I may preſent you a chaſt virgine to Chriſt:</hi> Now this being ſo, Chriſt being moſt glorious and honourable, his people muſt needs be ſo; For as the Lawyers ſpeak, <hi>Uxor fulget radiis mariti,</hi> The wife alwaies ſhares in, and ſhines with the rayes of her husbands honour. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 16. We ſee that Chriſts ſpirituall ſeed, ſuch are all true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, are Princes in all lands.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Plut.</note> 2. Their ſervice is moſt honourable becauſe Gods ſervice. Among men to perform the meaneſt office about the perſon of a Prince, is rightly judged honourable; The title of a ſervant of God is an higher title, then that of Monarch of the World, as <hi>Numa</hi> King of <hi>Rome</hi> once ſaid. The higheſt ſtile that King <hi>David</hi> could deviſe to give himſelf, not in the phraſe of a frivolous <hi>French</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, but in the plain ſpeech of a true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> was <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 16. <hi>Oh Lord truely I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant;</hi> He doubles it, becauſe he knew not poſſibly how to adde an higher and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter title.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their Guard is moſt honourable. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>Are they not all miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter to them that ſhall be heirs of ſalvation!</hi> The interrogation is to be reſolved into this Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Are they not all (viz.)</hi> the Angels <hi>miniſtring Spirits, &amp;c. that is, they are certainly.</hi> The God of glory himſelf hath not more noble creatures to wait on his own glorious Majeſty. Amongſt men tis counted an high piece of reſpect, when ſome perſon high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpected by the Prince takes leave of him, to ſend ſome of his principall Courtiers to accompany him the length of a room, or <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 7. Pſal. 94. 11.</note>Court-yard; but all the precious people of God ſtirre not one ſtep, without this glorious, although inviſible guard of an Angel, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, (I ſpeak nothing of the ſafety of this guard, which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably ſtronger, then a guard of many armed men, although never ſo well armed and ordered) Graceleſſe nobles have often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a company of vile men like themſelves waiting on them, as if their own perſonal ſins were not ſufficiently provoking, but they muſt have their idle, drunken, and ſwearing ſervants by their ſins
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58289:12"/>
alſo, as with cartropes, to draw down ſpeedy and fearfull venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon them. One of the Saints guard is able to prevail againſt many thouſands of ungodly ones, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. 36. <hi>Then the angel of the Lord went forth, and ſmote in the camp of the Aſſyrians one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fourſcore and five thouſand, and when they aroſe early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behold they were all dead corpſes.</hi> But all the holy ones of God <note place="margin">Pſ. 103. 20.</note>are attended by holy and mighty Angels who <hi>excel in ſtrength,</hi> and never want will to be ſerviceable to the people of God to their beſt advantage according to divine appointment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The condition of thoſe that make the godly mans Choice is unqueſtionably the moſt comfortable condition. I the rather touch upon this, becauſe it hath been, is, and will be a ſlander uſed by wicked men to diſcourage others from the good <note place="margin">Spiritus Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſticus eſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicus.</note>ways of God, to aſſert the inconſiſtency of ſtrictneſs in an holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion with a chearful, and comfortable converſation: As if as ſoon as a Chriſtians name and heart is really given up to God, he muſt ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly bid adue to all true joy and delight: The falſeneſſe of that imputation brought againſt the precious ways of God, I ſhall endeavour to diſcover and confute by making good theſe two Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That true and great joy is found in Gods wayes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such joy can no where elſe be obtained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The joy of Chriſtians in the wayes of God, is a true and a great joy. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Her wayes are wayes of pleaſantneſſe, and all her pathes are peace;</hi> They are ſtrewed with roſes, and paved with peace. Some degree of comfort followes every good action, as heat accompanies fire, as beames and influences iſſue from the ſun; Which is ſo true, that very heathens upon the diſcharge of a good conſcience have found comfort, and peace anſwerable, which if it had been the comfort of a conſcience purified by the bloud of Chriſt, it had been <hi>praemium ante praemium,</hi> a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reward of well-doing, in doing whereof (not only for doing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) there is great reward, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 11. Tis impoſſible that thoſe wayes ſhould be uncomfortable where the work of walking in them is wages to it ſelf. We ſee here that God by the mouth of <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that the <hi>ways of wiſdome,</hi> that is, of Chriſt the wiſdome of the father, <hi>are ways of pleaſantneſſe,</hi> and all her pathes, not only ſome of them, are peace. This being ſo, it matters not although the wicked men in the world ſhould ſay, and ſwear that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58289:13"/>
they are uncomfortable ways: The Apoſtle declares what our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in ſuch a caſe, namely to believe God, and not men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 4, <hi>Let God be true, and every man a liar;</hi> And if we conſult the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1. 8. we ſhall find the greatneſſe of the godly mans joy aſſerted. <hi>Whom having not ſeen, ye love, in whom, though now ye ſee him not, yet believing, ye rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Leighs ſoules ſolace againſt ſorrow.</note>Oh the joyes! the joyes! the joyes! that I feel in my ſoul! they be wonderful, they be wonderful, they be wonderful; were the words of Miſtreſſe <hi>Katherine Brettergh.</hi> And another, Oh the joy! the joy! the unexpreſſible joy that I find in my ſoul! The truth is, theſe joys are beſt known by experience; The beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that can be uſed, is not ſufficient for the full expreſſion of <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 8.</note>them: And therefore holy <hi>David</hi> wiſely provokes others to get a taſte of Gods goodneſſe themſelves, for that would more prevaile with them to admire, and preferre Gods comforts before all other comforts whatſoever, then never ſo many high expreſſions uttered by thoſe who have the feeling of them, for it is in this caſe, as it is with one, who taſtes honey he is more ſatisfied by the taſte of its ſweetneſſe, then if he ſhould hear the learned diſcourſes of an hundred Philoſophers concerning it. We have now briefly proved that the joy and comfort to be found in Gods ways, is true, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and great, we proceed to the ſecond Concluſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The joy of Chriſtleſſe perſons is not ſuch true, great, and glorious joy; I do not ſay, they have no joy, and comfort, I only aſſert, that their joy is not of that kind and excellent quality, with the joy of the Lords dear ones; Which for brevity's ſake I ſhall diſcover by comparing the comforts of thoſe who are intereſted in it, with thoſe that are ſtrangers to it, in four particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The joy of true Chriſtians, as Chriſtians, is a true, reall, and ſubſtantial joy; <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9. 3. the joy of Gods people is compared to <hi>the joy of harveſt,</hi> and the joy of thoſe <hi>that divide the ſpoil.</hi> Now what joys are more reall and enlarged that can be found amongſt the children of men! The husband man after all his great coſt, paines, and patience, when he lives to ſee a plentifull harveſt doth not onely ſeem, but doth really, and exceedingly rejoyce. The Souldier that a little while ſince was horribly affrighted, with the roaring of Cannons, and the fatal falls of many on his right and left hand, after the battel is over, himſelf in ſafety, and dividing the rich ſpoiles of his enemy: Who is ſo ſenſeleſſe as to doubt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58289:13"/>
of the reality of his joy! or ſo eloquent as to expreſſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it: So reall and great, yea much more, is the joy of the precious people of God. But on the other ſide, the joy of the wicked is moſtly in appearance, not in reality, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 12. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the falſe hearted <hi>Corinthians,</hi> gives this remarkable Character of them, <hi>That they glory in appearance, and not in heart.</hi> Their ſervices are hypocritical, and ſo are their joyes. And tis moſt juſt with God to ſuffer it to be ſo. For ſhame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O ye ſonnes of vanity, boaſt not of that joy, which is but skin deep, which is but the hypocriſy of mirth, your laughter is but grinning, your hearts often times ake terribly when your impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent faces counterfeit a ſmile. Learn, learn before it be too late, holily to abhorre that mirth which is ſo frothy, and flaſhy, which onely ſmoothes the brow, but fills not the breaſt, which onely wets the mouth, but cannot warm and chear the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The joy of Gods holy ones is high and noble.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is an heaven-born birth, and conſequently proceeds from the higheſt and moſt noble efficient. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit is joy.</hi> God the holy Ghoſt is the worker, and preſerver of a Chriſtians joy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When Chriſtians rejoyce their higheſt faculties are exerciſed upon the higheſt objects poſſible, not ſenſuall objects, ſuch as beaſts can rejoyce in, nor meerly rational, ſuch as well-bred Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens can excell in, but ſpiritual, and ſupernatural objects, then which none can be found more noble, or ſo noble. This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by thoſe words of the Church, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61. 10. <hi>I will greatly rejoyce in the Lord, my ſoul ſhall be joyful in my God, for he hath clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed me with the garments of ſalvation, he hath covered me with the robe of righteouſneſſe, as a bridegroom decketh himſelf with ornaments, and as a bride adorneth her ſelf with jewels;</hi> So that it is evident, that not riches, but righteouſneſſe, not the vanities of this world, but the concernments of the other world, are the noble objects, of Chriſtians joyes. Let us now glance upon the low, ſordid, and bruitiſh objects of worldlings joyes, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 16. <hi>And he ſpake a parable unto them, ſaying, the ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully,</hi> verſ. 17. <hi>And he thought within himſelf, ſaying, what ſhall I do, becauſe I have no room where to beſtow my fruits. And he ſaid,</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>This will I do, I will pull down my barns, and build greater, and there will I beſtow all my fruits, and my goods,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58289:14"/>
verſ. 19. <hi>And I will ſay to my ſoul, ſoul, thou haſt much goods layd up for many years, take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry,</hi> verſ. 20. <hi>But God ſaid to him, Thou fool,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe words we ſee the low objects of the worldlings joy, the Creatures, not the Creator, their goods on earth, not the God of heaven, food and drink are for the body, which is the bruitiſh part; In the 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> we ſee the right cenſure of God upon this perſon, he cals him <hi>Fool,</hi> and ſo he was, becauſe he onely minded ſuch low and periſhing objects, his barns being a fitter object for his hoggs then for himſelf to delight in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The joy of Chriſtians is a ſtrong joy. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 18. It <note place="margin">Neh. 8. 10.</note>is called <hi>ſtrong conſolation,</hi> and it makes the people of God ſtrong, even to admiration of all obſervers. It is reported of one <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> that ſeeing the Martyrs very comfortable when ſuffering ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grievous torments, he asked one of them the cauſe, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that live him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 9. The naming of which Text ſo wrought upon him, that afterwards he became a Martyr. In 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 4. Afflicted <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth himſelf thus; <hi>I am filled with comfort, I am exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyful in all our tribulation.</hi> Verſ. 5. <hi>For when we were come into Macedonia, our fleſh had no reſt, but we were troubled on every ſide, without were <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ightings, within were fears.</hi> Verſ. 6. <hi>Nevertheleſſe God that comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, comforted us by the coming of Titus.</hi> The joy of Chriſtians like oyl gets above all the deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of adverſity. Tis to admiration, how even weak women and children in time of perſecution, having their hearts ſtrengthned with Gods joy, have endured ſuch grievous torments with ſuch triumphant gallantneſſe of ſpirit, that their enemies were more weary of infflicting, then they of enduring thoſe grievous things wherewith they were tried. And tis well known, that ſome of the great ones of the world, in diſcontent have layd down their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, becauſe they could not conquer Chriſtians by torments. But as for the joy of the wicked, it is very weak: Many birds can ſing a ſcurvey note in ſummer time, but in winter they are gone; ſuch is the joy of the wicked in proſperity, then they ſpeak high, and look merrily, but the leaſt croſſe almoſt marrs their mirth, and puts them into their dumps. There is more whining, and crying with ſome Chriſtleſſe perſon for the loſſe of a Cow, Horſe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58289:14"/>
nay ſometimes for a ſmall Pig, then of thirty or fourty years re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt God. Alas, their weak comforts are eaſily overtopt, they lie at the mercy almoſt of every thing, the frown of a rich neighbour, the plague at the next family, the fall of a market make many of them ſigh, and groan like dying men; and if they at any time hear a terrible clap of thunder, like <hi>Caligula,</hi> they are ready to crawl under their beds, as frighted wormes wriggle into their dark holes. I might eaſily give many remarkable inſtances of the different behaviour of the godly and ungodly under the ſame kind of affliction. I ſhall name but one in this haſt, and that is the affliction of ſcarcity, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 17, 18. <hi>Although the fig-tree ſhall not bloſſom, neither ſhall fruit be in the vines, the labour of the olives ſhall fail, and the fields ſhall yeild no meat, the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no herd in the ſtalls,</hi> Verſ. 18. <hi>Yet I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my ſalvation.</hi> Here we have a bleſſed pattern for our imitation, when under afflictions, The Prophet <hi>Habbakuk</hi> prayed, believed, rejoyced; But in a like caſe wicked men carry themſelves not like godly perſons, but like bruit creatures, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>And they have not cried unto me with their hearts, when they howled upon their beds: They aſsemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for corn and wine, and they rebell againſt me:</hi> Under their ſcarcity no right praying, believing, rejoycing, but rebelling againſt God, and howling like a company of ſtarved dogs. O the glorious and invincible ſtrength of true Chriſtian joy! O the weak and vaniſhing joy of all Chriſtleſſe perſons in the day of trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If we conſider the difference between the joy of the wicked, and godly in point of duration, it will be very remarkable. If you come and ask a Saint, poſſeſſed of that noble heaven-born joy before mentioned, ſaying; Friend, how long will this joy of yours laſt! He may anſwer, and make good his anſwer after this manner, My glorious joy which is unſpeakable, ſhall laſt as long as I would have it to laſt, It ſhall endure as long as any thing on earth, or in heaven endureth, It ſhall run parrallel with the longeſt line of Gods eternity: This is fully proved from thoſe words, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, which hath loved us, and given us everlaſting conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> God is an everlaſting God, and his peoples conſolation is everlaſting. Tis true the ſunne of a Chriſtians joy in this life may
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58289:15"/>
be clouded with temptations, and deſertions; but yet it is moſt certain that ſooner or later all theſe clouds ſhall be ſcattered, and their joy appear as glorious, yea more glorious then ever before. The dark clouds may for a while keep in the bright beames of the ſunne, that it ſhines not out ſo comfortably as at other times: but ſtill it is not, cannot by this meanes be pulled out of its Orbe. Tis ſo with a Chriſtians joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30. 5. <hi>Weeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.</hi> Eſa. 54. 7. <hi>For a ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have I forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee.</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment, but with everlaſting kindneſſe will I have mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy redeemer.</hi> But come and propound the like queſtion to a Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſon, although in the moſt proſperous condition in reſpect of fullneſſe of riches, height of honour, variety of all the choiceſt delights of the children of men; that ever any ſuch perſon hath enjoyed, or can enjoy in that ſtate; and you ſhall ſee what a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if true anſwer muſt be returned, when you ask, how long his joy ſhall laſt! It may be ſome wicked man may dream, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently utter thoſe golden dreams, that his condition ſhall be comfortable in both worlds: There are very many, too many ſuch dreamers in all corners of the world; But you muſt remember, I told you that, although many wicked men ſay, yet no wicked man living can prove any ſuch thing as this, that his joy ſhall continue with him in both worlds, or that it ſhall abide with him ſo long as he lives in this world. When the wicked depart out of this life, they muſt everlaſtingly bid adieu to all true joy and comfort, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 11. <hi>The ſmoak of their torments aſcends for ever, and they have no reſt night nor day.</hi> But many of them begin their hell here, long before their tranſlation hence, as the godly their heaven. A wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man though in never ſo flouriſhing, and proſperous condition in the eye of ſenſe, or reaſon, cannot upon good ground be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that his peace, and comfort ſhall continue one week, or day or hour longer, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 6. <hi>For as the crackling of thorns under a pot,</hi> which make a ſhort blaze, and is ſuddenly extinct, <hi>ſo is the laughter of a fool;</hi> Such God accounts, and calls all wicicked men. <note place="margin">Amos. 8. 9.</note>The Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> tels the wicked, that <hi>their ſun ſhall go down at noon day.</hi> All the wicked mans conſiderable joy may be over, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore half his dayes be paſſed; God delights to marre the mirth of Chriſtleſs ones in the midſt of their jollity; <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58289:15"/>
of the Chapter, we read that King <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> made a great feaſt for a thouſand of his Lords; and himſelf, his Princes, wives and concubines were upon their merry pinnes, quaffing, and carowſing in golden and ſilver veſſels, taken out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: But we read in <hi>v.</hi> 5. that all this joy was turned ſuddenly into extream ſadneſſe. <hi>In the ſame hour came forth fingers of a mans hand, and wrote over againſt the Candleſtick upon the playſter of the wall of the Kings Pallace, and the King ſaw the part of the hand that wrote.</hi> v. 6. <hi>Then the Kings countenance was changed, and his thoughts troubled him, ſo that the joynts of his loynes were looſed, and his knees ſmote one against another.</hi> v. 7. <hi>Then the King cried aloud,</hi> &amp;c. Oh the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſſe of that ſhort liv'd joy which a wicked man cannot be rightly confident to enjoy for the ſmall ſpace of one poor hour. <note place="margin">Job. 20. 5.</note>Theſe things premiſed, if any perſon wiſh well to his own joy, no choice, but the Chriſtians choice is the right way to obtain, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it in both worlds.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Chriſtians choice is as unqueſtionably the beſt, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the concernments of the other world. It cannot be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably expected, that in a piece of an hour I ſhould goe over in my diſcourſe the ſtate of the Saints bleſſedneſſe in Heaven, and the ſinners miſery in Hell, that by comparing them together, it may be diſcovered which choice is beſt, that which leads to Heaven's happineſſe, or Hell's miſery. This may abundantly ſuffice for my preſent purpoſe, to mention four remarkable Particulars, which hold forth light enough convincingly to prove the concluſion I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered about this weighty point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Godly mans choice will infallibly bring him to ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a condition in the other world, that he ſhall not deſire, or have cauſe to deſire any other good, then that he ſhall then be poſſeſſed of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25. The Pſalmiſt expreſſeth himſelf thus, <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee! and there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee!</hi> If this be the language of the Saints in this world, ſurely there will be much more cauſe why it ſhould be their <note place="margin">In beatudine complebitur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne deſiderium beatorum, <hi>Aquinas.</hi>
               </note>conſtant language in the other world. God is the univerſal good, and they will then be in the fulleſt enjoyment of it, that their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are capable of; and ſo there will be no need of the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of any other good below God to perfect their ſubſtantial happineſſe. That ſea of goodneſſe will ſurely fill brim-ful all their largeſt veſſels. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. laſt <hi>verſ. Thou wilt ſhew me the path
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58289:16"/>
of life, in thy preſence is fullneſſe of joy,</hi> and ſo no room for any other objects: But as for all the wicked their woful caſe will be far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then their moſt afflicted eſtate ever was in this life. In this world ſuch is the admirable kindneſſe of the glorious God to his curſed, adverſaries that he ſeems to deal with them more like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then like enemies. The Pſalmiſt tels us, that in this life, <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 7.</note>
               <hi>they have more good things then heart could wiſh.</hi> Here, when they are in pain, or any other affliction, many of them can ſay to their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; Call my dear husband, or wife, to refreſh me with their company: Bid my beloved Child, or faithfull Friend, come and be helpfull to me: Go fetch me ſuch a coſtly Cordial, to keep up my fainting ſpirits: But in the other world, God affords them no ſuch comforts. Their cup of gall and wormwood have not the leaſt drop of any comfortable ingredient to qualifie the bitterneſſe thereof, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 25. But <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, <hi>Son, remember, that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things, and likewiſe Lazarus evil things, but now he is comforted, &amp; thou art tormented.</hi> Wicked men have all the comfortable portion that they are like to receive from God, in <note place="margin">Pſal 17. 14.</note>this life; no wonder therefore when death comes, they are ſoloth to depart hence. The requeſt made was but for a very ſmall courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. a finger dipt in water would have been but a poor meanes to abate the paines of his tongue tormented with helliſh flames; yet as ſmall as it was, it was denied, to let all Chriſtleſſe perſons know, what they muſt truſt to in the other world. They muſt onely drink of the wine of the wrath of God without mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not the leaſt drop of mercy ſhall be mingled with it. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The condition of all godly perſons in the other world, ſhall be much more comfortable, then they can poſſibly conceive while they are in this life. Oh how happy would many judge their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to be, if all that they could poſſibly conceive to be delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them, might be enjoyed by them! But the caſe of all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified perſons ſhall be far more comfortable then this comes to, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, nor hath it entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 John 3. 2.</note>
               <hi>love him.</hi> It never entred into the hearts of God; beſt people here to conceive fully, how happy their glorified condition ſhall be: Their happineſſe ſhall be made up of ſuch ingredients, which the infinitely wiſe God, who prepared it ſhall judge to be moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58289:16"/>
and ſure infinite wiſdome can beſt chooſe the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ingredients, and his infinite love to his people, will not ſuffer him to leave out any of them. But now on the other ſide, the waies that wicked ones chooſe, will bring them to greater wo and miſery in the other world, then they can for the preſent fully conceive, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 11. <hi>Who knoweth the power of thy wrath?</hi> The interrogation is to be reſolved into this negation; None can fully conceive the greatneſſe of it. We may conceive that it will be very dreadful, and although we know not to the utmoſt how dreadful it will be, 'twill certainly be intollerable, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 15, 16, 17. <hi>And the Kings of the earth, and the great men, and the rich men, and the chief Captains, and the mighty men, and every bond-man, and every free-man hid themſelves in the Dens, and in the rocks of the mountaines, and ſaid to the mountaines and rocks, fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.</hi> This was a poor ſhelter, for the mountains melt, and the rocks rend at his angry preſence, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand! Oh woful, and miſerable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, who can neither abide, nor avoid the fearful wrath of God! It would be very ſad news to a wicked man, if one ſhould come and tell him, that that perſon who hateth him moſt of all others in the world, hath power over him, and is deviſing all the horrid torments that the wit of man can imagine, which ſhall ſhortly be inflicted upon him; But alas all this is but a very ſmall thing (I had almoſt ſaid a very nothing in point of terrour) If it be compared with what terrible and true tidings I am now from God to acquaint all Chriſtleſſe perſons with. Although you who are wicked do often pretend (as thoſe liars the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeakes of) much love to your God, with your lips, yet I am ſure, he doth not believe you; But he who knoweth your hearts better then your ſelves ſaith, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 8. that his ſoul loathes you, and your ſoules abhorre him; And if you die in this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the miſery which you ſhall endure in the other world ſhall be, not what the finite underſtanding of one no nor ten thouſand an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry malicious men, laying their heads together can deviſe to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute upon you; but what the infinite underſtanding of that God who loathes you, hath prepared to render your condition moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely, unſpeakably, and unconceivably miſerable. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41. <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the devil
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58289:17"/>
and his angels.</hi> There is the doleful emphaſis of the miſery of damned perſons in the other world; Their miſery was prepared by the infinite wiſdom of God, who beſt knowes what ingredients are moſt torturing, and his infinite hatred of their ſinful perſons will not ſuffer him to leave out the leaſt of them. They have vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">Iſa. 63. 10. Ezek. 16. 43. and 32. 9.</note>and fretted Gods ſoul by their ſins here, and God will vex eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vein of their hearts, and be revenged on them to the utmoſt hereafter. Hiſtories mention many waies of torment which the heatheniſh and antichriſtian factions have invented, to diſcover their curſed rage againſt the precious people of God; As plates of iron burning hot, which they have laid upon their naked fleſh, pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers red hot with which they have pulled off the fleſh from the bones, bodkins with which they have pricked their bodies all over caſting them into Lime-kilns, and into Caldrons of ſcalding lead, their skins were flead off alive, and their raw fleſh rubbed with ſalt and vineger, they were laid upon Gridirons, roſted and baſted with ſalt and vineger, their bodies were rent aſunder by faſtning them to boughs of trees, they were toſſed upon the horns of Bulls with their bowels hanging out, they were tortured on the rack, on the wheel, and on the gibbet with flaming fire under them. Theſe were very grievous waies of torment; But alas, theſe and many more ſuch deviſes, were no more then the inventions and executions of finite men, which God permitted to be uſed upon the bodies of the people who were dearly beloved of his ſoul, and therefore are but as bug-bears to ſcare children, if they be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with that moſt fearful vengeance which an infinite God hath decreed to execute upon all Chriſtleſſe perſons in the other world; Becauſe of the infinite hatred that is in his ſoul againſt them. In ſhort, The happines of heaven will be much more ſweet, then the people of God can conceive, while they are here, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of hell will be much more dreadful then the wicked, in this life, either did or could poſſibly imagine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Godly in the life to come ſhall have onely ſuch company as they would have. Man is a ſociable creature, therefore ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſociety is a delight, &amp;c. This will be a very conſiderable ingredient in that happineſſe. Here they cry out, or have cauſe continually to cry out in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. 5. <hi>Wo is me that I ſojourn in Meſhech, that I dwell in the tents of Kedar</hi> Little doth the wicked ones of the world know and conſider,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58289:17"/>
what an heart-breake they are to their godly neighbours, and near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt relations, becauſe of the wicked courſes which they take. It is with them as it was with <hi>Lot,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7, 8. Their righteous ſoules are vexed from day to day with ſeeing and hearing of their unlawful deeds. But hereafter they ſhall be in that place where no ſuch perſons ſhall have leave to appear, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 27. <hi>There ſhall in no wiſe enter into it, any thing that defileth, neither that worketh abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or maketh a lie.</hi> No dirty Dog ſhall ſet footing on that pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Glory. In heaven thou ſhalt enjoy higheſt communion with God the Father, who elected thee, God the Son who redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee, and God the holy Ghoſt, who ſanctified and comforted thee: Then ſhalt thou be in the company of innumerable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who have done thee more good offices then ever thou tookeſt notice of, and the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect; Here it is ſweet, yea very ſweet to enjoy the company of one or two godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, what will it be then, to be in the company of all the righteous that ever were, are, or ſhall be? Here the beſt of Chriſtians are imperfect in their knowledge, love, and all other graces; and yet wiſe, and holy <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe <hi>rather to ſuffer affliction with them, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon, eſteeming the reproach of Chriſt greater riches, then the treaſures of Aegypt, for he had reſpect to the recompence of reward,</hi> Heb. 11. 25, 26. But ſure the company of Gods people, when there is no ignorance, envy, frowardneſſe, or any other corruption, will be much more deſirable. But on the other ſide the company of thoſe that make not this choice will be a very great part of their torment; they muſt depart into the place where the devil and his angels are, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41. Here if men do but fancy the apparition of one devil to them, they look pale, their hair ſtands up, they ſhriek terribly, and are ready to drop down dead: What will their woful caſe be in the midſt of the devils really abiding with them? Here wicked ones have many perſons, as husbands, wives, children, friends, that are the delight of their eyes, and the joy of their hearts; But in the other world it would be a very great abatement of their miſery, if they might never ſee any of them that remain Chriſtleſſe as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do. A great many think they have done all that belongs to them, if they provide eſtates for their relations, wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to live gallantly in the world, but never take the leaſt care about their ſoules, more precious then the world: But when they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58289:18"/>
meet together before Chriſts Tribunal, may not many women with better warrant ſay to their husbands then <hi>Moſes</hi> wife did to him, <hi>Thou haſt been a bloudy husband to me;</hi> And many children, Oh thou cruel Father, if you had (according to your duty) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, corrected, and given me an holy example, I had never been ſo ſinful and ſo miſerable as now I am: And ſo ſervants cry out bitterly, Oh that I had never entered within the door of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of ſuch a graceleſſe Maſter, who in ſtead of helping me to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, haled me with violence to the pit of deſtruction. On earth tis a common ſpeech amongſt the wicked, <hi>The more the merrier,</hi> not ſo in hell, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 21. <hi>Then he ſaid, I pray therefore, father, that thou wouldeſt ſend him to my fathers houſe, for I have five brethren, that he may teſtifie unto them, leaſt they alſo come into this place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> I cannot be ſo charitable, as to think, ſo good a thing as Charity dwels among the damned crew: But he knew that if they came to hell, his torments would be the greater, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired never to ſee them more. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 12. They that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry in the other world, they weep and gnaſh their teeth: The more therefore who are damned, the louder and more hideous roaring, and the greater number of ghaſtly, and frightful perſons, <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 41.</note>who gnaſh their teeth. The ſaints in the life to come ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be afflicted with any unacceptable company for a day hour or moment, and the wicked ſhall never be refreſhed with a pleaſing companion, although it be but for the leaſt ſpace of time which is imaginable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All the godly perſons ſhall enjoy the comfortable condition before mentioned to all eternity; and all the wicked ſhall endure that woful miſery for ever. This great big-bellied Epithet, <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall;</hi> is that which heightens happines, or miſery to the utmoſt. I begin with the firſt branch. The Saints happineſſe will be, and they ſhall know that it will be everlaſting. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 11. <hi>In thy preſence is fulneſſe of joy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> This proves the joy of glorified ones ſhall be everlaſting. And if we look into 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 17. we may obſerve <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking in the name of believers, <hi>We which are alive and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air, and ſo we ſhall be ever with the Lord.</hi> And if the Saints in this life know, that their happineſſe ſhall be everlaſting, in the life to come, ſurely the knowledge of the ſaints Triumphant is not leſſe, then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58289:18"/>
the knowledge of the ſaints Militant: this being ſo, that their happineſſe ſhall be everlaſting, and they know it ſhall be ſo. The Apoſtle might well adde, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Wherefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another with theſe words.</hi> It is not poſſible, or needful that more comfortable words ſhould be ſpoken to any of the Children of men. <hi>Ubi eſt ſummum bonum, ibi ſumma faelicitas, ſumma jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas, vera libertas, perfecta charitas, aeterna ſecuritas, &amp; ſecura aeternitas.</hi> Bernard, Medit. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Now as for the wicked, Eternity is that which renders their condition amazingly, unſpeakably, and unconceivably woful, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 33. 14. <hi>The ſinners in Sion are afraid, fearfulneſſe hath ſurprized the hypocrites.</hi> What is the matter! There follow two hard Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Who ſhall dwell with devouring fire,</hi> although for a ſhort ſpace of time! But the hardeſt Queſtion of all is, <hi>Who ſhall endure everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burnings!</hi> If the damned in hell could in truth ſay (which they cannot) I have been roaring, and yelling many years in this burning lake, but after ſo many hundred, or thouſand years I ſhall certainly be delivered out of this place of Torment; The thoughts of being delivered, although after a long time would wonderfully abate their miſery: But when they ſpeak that which is the truth in this caſe. Here I have been a great while, weeping, and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my teeth, and ſo muſt be for ever. This Eternity is (as I may ſo ſpeak) The very hell of hell. What more confounding words ever did or can God ſpeak, or wicked ones hear, then thoſe words which God will ere long pronounce in their hearing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41. <hi>Depart ye our ſed into everlaſting fire.</hi> When the wicked have been in hell as many years as there are hairs on their heads, ſtars in the firmament, or ſands upon the Sea-ſhore, they are as farre from the end of their torments, as they were the firſt moment they dropt into the burning lake.</p>
            <p>I have now diſpatch't the Demonſtration of the Doctrine, by which it clearly appears, that in reference to all the concernments of both worlds, The godly mans choice is unqueſtionably and incomparably the beſt choice that can be made.</p>
            <p>The third thing that I promiſed, was to vindicate this glorious Doctrine from the Objections, and Cavils that are brought againſt it; to name them all, were a very long, if poſſible task. I ſhall take notice of two principal ones, which being clearly propounded, and fully anſwered, I ſhall haſten to the Application.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58289:19"/>
               <hi>Object.</hi> The Scripture declares, That the Choice you ſpeak of will infallibly expoſe us to many Afflictions, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 22. <hi>We muſt through much tribulation enter into the kingdom of God.</hi> Let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God walk never ſo wiſely and holily, there is no avoiding of the Croſſe: If any think to go to Heaven without tribulation, he muſt (as the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine</hi> told the Heretick <hi>Aceſias.)</hi> erect a ladder, and go up alone. Now the Apoſtle tels us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>No chaſtning for the preſent ſeems to be joyous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but grievous:</hi> How then can that choice be ſo much approved, that renders our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo grievous in this world!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Before I Anſwer this Objection, I muſt premiſe, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this and a thouſand ſuch Objections framed by Satan, or his inſtruments, cannot prevailingly alter the choice of any, that have in truth given up their names and hearts to God, and his precious waies, yet needleſſe diſcouragements may be upon their ſpirits by means thereof. Again, This conſideration of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that they who walk in Gods waies meet with, may diſhearten others from making this choice, when invited and provoked to enter into the way of life. I ſhall therefore give in ſomething by way of anſwer, for the ſatisfaction of both theſe ſort of perſons, who are herein concerned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. To take off the diſcouragements of thoſe who have made this holy and happy choice the Text ſpeaks of. I can in this haſte name but a few things (but I hope enough for their relief) to be conſidered by them. I do not, dare not deny, That the way to heaven is through much tribulation, becauſe the Scripture in the aforementioned place elſewhere doth ſo fully aſſert it. But withall I may adde that this very doctrine hath been judged by Chriſtians to be no ſuch uncomfortable doctrine, as the Objection before mentioned ſeems to hold forth; yea we may gather from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of ſome eminent ones, that they would rather have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the contrary an uncomfortable doctrine: as holy <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. &amp; Mon.</note>who ſaid, that if there were any way to heaven on horſeback, it was by affliction. And another we read of in the Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, who profeſſed, that if any thing was abated of his affliction, it was to his loſſe: and ſincere <hi>Saunders</hi> could ſay, <hi>I am in priſon, till I am in priſon:</hi> and a fourth, <hi>The more pain, the more gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let me entreat you to conſider, what may be obſerved out of <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 11.</note>this very Text (to omit others) to anſwer the Objection: It is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58289:19"/>
not ſaid, Chaſtiſements are grievous, but <hi>ſeem grievous.</hi> Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are indeed grievous to outward ſenſe, and in that reſpect it is here ſaid, that chaſtiſements ſeem grievous. But when ſenſe feels grief, faith may, and often doth conceive abundance of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>James</hi> 1. 2. Believing <hi>James</hi> could ſay, that we muſt <hi>count it all joy when we fall into divers temptations.</hi> The world wondreth, ſaith Mr. <hi>Philpot</hi> the Martyr, how we can be merry in ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream miſery; But our God is omnipotent, who turneth miſery <note place="margin">Act. &amp; Mon.</note>into felicity. Believe me there is no ſuch joy in the world, as the people of God have under the Croſſe; I ſpeak it by experience: And for thoſe who are ſo tender and delicate profeſſors of Religion, that their ſenſes muſt by no means be offended, I might ſend them to ſchool to abundance of Heathens, who would make them bluſh to ſpeak of ſuch womaniſh and childiſh tenderneſſe. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxarchus,</hi> when he was commanded by a Tyrant to be put into a mortar, cries out to his perſecutors, Ye do but beat the veſſel of <hi>Anaxarchus,</hi> he accounted the affliction of his body no ſuch great matter: and our Lord ſpeaks fully to this point, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 28. <hi>Fear not them which can kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoul.</hi> The worſt that the worſt of incarnate devils can do to the people of God, is but to put the body to pain, and not alwaies that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without Gods permiſſion: For holy <hi>Bainham</hi> at the ſtake, and in the midſt of the flame (which had half conſumed his arms <note place="margin">Acts &amp; Monu.</note>and legs) ſpake theſe words, <hi>O ye Papiſts, ye look for miracles, here you may ſee a miracle, for in this fire I feel no more pain, then if I were in a bed of Down; but it is to me as a bed of Roſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The grievous afflictions of the people of God are mitigated by the limitation of time; they are but for the preſent time of this life; ſo that, the ſhortneſſe may exceedingly comfort againſt the ſharpneſs of them. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Now for a ſeaſon (if need be) ye are in heavineſſe through manifold temptations.</hi> We read in the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Lamentations,</hi> that the Church was ſo deeply afflicted, that ſhe was filled with bitterneſſe, <hi>v.</hi> 15. and made drunk with worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <hi>v.</hi> 31. We ſee what was her great and ſufficient cordial to keep her from fainting: <hi>The Lord will not caſt off for ever,</hi> as if ſhe had ſaid, This bitterneſſe is not everlaſting bitterneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſo overwhelming.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The many excellent fruits of ſanctified afflictions of Gods people, may ſufficiently comfort againſt the grievouſneſſe of them.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58289:20"/>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>Nevertheleſſe afterward it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſſe unto them which are exerciſed thereby.</hi> Here Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conceive, that by <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> we are to underſtand the ſame thing that is called holineſſe in <hi>v.</hi> 10. there is one glorious effect of ſanctified afflictions; and then this affliction is amplified by a ſpecial Epithete, <hi>Peaceable,</hi> that is, Chaſtiſement when ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied worketh peace in Chriſtians, and that is double, Internal in this world, and Eternal in the world to come. A word of each of theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sanctified afflictions are made uſe of by God for the encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the grace; of his people, this is Gods end. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>He chaſteneth us for our profit, that we may be partakers of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and he never fals ſhort of his ends. The Roſe is ſweeter in the Still, then on the ſtalk; the like difference is to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, when under, and out of affliction. <hi>John</hi> 15. 2. <hi>Every branch in me my Father purgeth, that it may bring forth more fruit:</hi> As Vines are made fruitfull by pruning, ſo are Gods people by his pruning knife of afflictions. Methinks this ſhould be enough to quiet and cheer up Gods people under the ſoreſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. We are not barely contented, but very thankfull, and willingly part with our money to Phyſitians that give us bitter purges, and Chyrurgians, that put us to great pain by launcing our fleſh, that ſo the diſeaſes and wounds of our bodies may be cured, and ſweet bodily health reſtored: We ought much more upon the account of our ſpiritual welfare, be not only contented under, but very thankfull for all Gods moſt ſmarting diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that tend to the reſtoring and preſerving our ſpiritual health.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sanctified afflictions are very uſefull for the procuring and preſerving of inward peace, this follows ſtrongly upon the former; for that which advanceth holineſſe, muſt needs procure peace. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 17. <hi>And the work of righteouſneſſe ſhall be peace,</hi> that is, the peace of conſcience <hi>which paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi> and is full of glory, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 7. This peace of God, like <hi>Davids</hi> Harp, driveth away the evil ſpirit of cares and fears, and ſoon huſheth all. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſuch is the wiſdom and indulgence of God to his afflicted children, that he deals with them, as we with ours. We are not prodigal of our Cordials, but give them only to our ſick, not healthfull children: ſo the Lord ſeeth that in time of great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58289:20"/>
his people moſt need, and will moſt prize his cordials, and then he pours them out freely. Many of the people of God know this by perſonal experiences; and if they had not drunk deeply of the cup of affliction, they had been ſtrangers to the ſenſe of thoſe ſtrong conſolations of the Goſpel. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 18. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 14. I will bring her into the wilderneſſe, and ſpeak comfortably to her. When Chriſtians are in a wilderneſſe condition in reſpect of ſuch afflictions, that they know not what way to turn, then God uſeth <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>to ſpeak kindly to them, yea to their very hearts, as the Original doth import.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſanctified afflictions of Gods people tend to their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal peace. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 17. they ſerve to ſweeten and greaten their glory in the other world. 1. To ſweeten it. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>The ſleep of a labouring man is ſweet:</hi> Sleep is the nurſe of nature, the wages ſhe paies the poor man for his unceſſant pains; theſe labouring men are no ſooner in bed, but the next thing is, they are faſt aſleep; their reſt is more uninterrupted than the reſt of others: So it is with the precious people of God, that all their lives long have been labouring hard in Gods furnace of affliction. It cannot be here fully conceived how ſweet the glorious reſt will be to them: <hi>Amaritudo praeeuntis doloris commendat ampliùs gaudia ſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura. Hier. ad virginem in exilium miſſam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Majora certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miaa majora ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia. <hi>Tert.</hi> ad Scap.</note> 2 To greaten their glory. The greater the combats, the greater are the following rewards of grace. <hi>Bernard</hi> cals the perſecutors, but his Fathers Gold-ſmiths, that are working to add Pearls to the glorious Crowns of Saints, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 18. <hi>For our light afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> Here is an elegant Antitheſis, and a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hyperbole beyond engliſhing. For affliction, here is glory; for light affliction, a weight of glory; for momentany affliction, eternal glory. But then thoſe words added, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are very remarkeable, An exceeding, exceſſive, or a far more excellent, will make the eternal weight of glory a juſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our largeſt admirations to all eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for thoſe who are afraid to chooſe the precious waies of God, becauſe of the grievous afflictions which have been menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and chooſe the waies of ſin to prevent troubles, they do as fooliſhly as they, who run into the fire thinking to prevent burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is impoſſible. To undeceive them, I ſhall at this time
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58289:21"/>
propound only theſe few Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Chooſe what way thou wilt, and take what courſe thou canſt, thou ſhalt certainly meet with afflictions, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 2. <hi>All things come alike to all. There is one event to the righteous and to the wicked, to the good, and to the clean, and to the unclean, to him that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth and to him that ſacrificeth not. As is the good, ſo is the ſinner, and he that ſweareth, as he that feareth an Oath.</hi> Look abroad in the world: What afflictions can be named, that are not found in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of the wicked, as well as in the habitations of the righteous? Are there not poor ſinners, as well as poor Saints, ſick unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as well as ſick believers? Are not the children of reprobates as perverſe, prodigal, and heart-breaking, as the children of Gods elect? <hi>Job</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Man is born to trouble as the ſparks fly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> As it is natural for the ſparks to fly upward, ſo it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral for every ſinful man to come forth in this world to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Before afflictions come, the ungodly have more cauſe to fear they will come upon them, than the godly, becauſe God in his Word hath made promiſes to deliver his people from all ſorts of afflicting evils, and hath threatned to bring all thoſe evils upon the wicked, as we may read at large, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 4. God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to bleſſe the fruit of the bodies of his ſervants. <hi>v.</hi> 18. He threatneth to curſe the fruit of the bodies of the wicked. <hi>v.</hi> 5. To bleſſe the basket and ſtore of his people. <hi>v.</hi> 17. To curſe the bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and ſtore of his adverſaries. <hi>v.</hi> 7. He promiſes to deliver his obedient children from their enemies. <hi>v.</hi> 25. He threatneth the contrary evil to thoſe that are diſobedient. And the like may be ſaid in many other inſtances in this Chapter, and elſewhere. All that can lightly be objected is, That the promiſes we are now ſpeaking of, are conditional; and that notwithſtanding theſe comfortable declarations of Gods favour to his dear ones, we ſee by experience that they are ſorely afflicted in their eſtates, poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and by cruel adverſaries. To this I briefly anſwer; Theſe temporal promiſes are conditional, but withal I muſt further add, The people of God do, and have cauſe cordially to approve thoſe Conditions.</p>
            <p>The only Conditions are theſe two,</p>
            <p n="1">1. God will vouchſafe all ſorts of temporal bleſſings privative, and poſitive to his people, unleſſe it be more for his own Glory to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58289:21"/>
deny them any of them. Now the Lords Grace which ſhould teach his ſervants to preferre his Glory above their ſpiritual and eternal good, doth teach them much more to preferre Gods Glory above their temporal good: Which they ſignifie, when accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt's preſcription, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 9. they underſtandingly pray, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name.</hi> There that petition which teaches to pray that God would order all things concerning themſelves, and all the reſt of the world, as may make moſt for his own Glory, is ſet before all other petitions that concern either their temporal, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or eternal good. And therefore in ſuch a caſe as holy <hi>Job,</hi> they can as cordially bleſs God for taking away children, and eſtate, as for giving them, <hi>Job</hi> 1. 21. <hi>God hath given, and God hath taken away, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The other condition is, God will give ſuch or ſuch temporal bleſſings to his dear people, unleſſe himſelf, who is beſt able to judge, ſee it moſt for their real advantage to want them. So the promiſe runs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 10. <hi>They that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing.</hi> They may be without many things, which, in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpeech they do not want: Now this being ſo, the people of God may charitably be ſuppoſed in cool blood to be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented under, nay, thankful for ſuch afflicting providences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by good things in themſelves, although not fit for them; are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held or removed from them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 10. One of the great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he uſeth to comfort the godly <hi>Hebrews</hi> under afflicting pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, was that I am now ſpeaking of, becauſe God afflicted them for their profit, that they might be partakers of his holineſs. Whatſoever is for our good, be it never ſo bitter, ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with thankfulneſſe, not ſullenneſſe. But now it may be pleaded alſo in reference to the wicked, that notwithſtanding all the threatnings in the Bible, abundance of wicked perſons are free from many of thoſe evils before-named all their daies.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are deeply indebted to God for his rich long ſuffering towards them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 22. <hi>God endures with much long ſuffering the veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They have no cauſe when all their accounts are rightly caſt up, to boaſt of their exemption. The leſſe they have ſuffered hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, the more is behind; their preſervation from leſſer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, are reſervations to greater future vengeance, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>The
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58289:22"/>
Lord knoweth how to deliver the righteous, and to reſerve the wicked to the day of judgment to be puniſhed. Origen</hi> in 8 <hi>hom.</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>I will not puniſh their daughters when they commit whoredam,</hi> expreſſeth himſelf thus, <hi>Vis indignantis Dei terribilem vocem audire,</hi> &amp;c. Wilt thou here the terrible voice of a provoked God! You ſhall be without chaſtiſement for a teſtimony that you <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 8.</note>are baſtards, not ſons. When was <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> condition ſo deſperate, as when God ſaid, <hi>My fury ſhall depart from thee, I will be quiet,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hîe ure; hîc ſeca modo in aeternum Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas. August.</note>
               <hi>and no more angry,</hi> Ezek. 16. 42. <hi>Fieri Domine, fieri,</hi> cried <hi>Luther,</hi> ſtrike Lord, ſtrike and ſpare not; <hi>ferre minora volo, ne graviora feram,</hi> I am willing to bear leſſer, that I may not bear greater evils. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> cals it <hi>miſericordiam omni indignatione crudeliorem,</hi> a moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and killing curteſie. <hi>Job</hi> accounted it a great favour to ſorry man, that God accounts him worth melting, although it be every morning, and trying, though it be every moment, <hi>Job</hi> 7. 17. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When the ſame kind and meaſure of outward evils do befal both the godly and ungodly, the condition of the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is abundantly more comfortable as in many other reſpects, ſo more eminently in theſe three, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. The motive,</cell>
                     <cell rows="3">of their troubles.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. The meaſure,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. The iſſue,</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What moves God to afflict his people?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the ſame precious love, which moved him to beſtow Jeſus Chriſt upon them to ſave them from wrath to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 19.</note>12. 6. <hi>For whom the Lord loveth, he chaſtiſeth, and ſcourgeth every ſon whom he receiveth.</hi> v. 7. <hi>If you endure chaſtning, God dealeth with you as with ſons.</hi> So that it is not common, but Fatherly love which moves God to afflict his children. But if the Queſtion be, Why doth God afflict wicked ones? another anſwer muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to wit, becauſe he beares ill will to them, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 8. <hi>My ſoul loathed them, and their ſoul abhorred me.</hi> Mark what followes immediately upon Gods abhorring them, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Then ſaid I, I will not feed you, that that dieth, let it die; and that that is to be cut off, let it be cut off; and let the reſt eat every one the fleſh of another.</hi> What moves God to bring poverty upon wicked men, becauſe God
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58289:22"/>
hates them, and cares not although they ſtarve. Why doth God ſend abundance of vexations into their Families? becauſe God ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors them, and grudges them Family-comforts! Wherefore doth he ſmite them with ſickneſſe, becauſe he loaths them, and ſo values nor their lives! They may die, and drop into hell as ſuddenly as may be, it ſhall be no trouble unto his heart: Here we ſee a moſt remarkable difference between thoſe who chuſe the waies of God, and thoſe who chooſe the waies of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 18. 11. <hi>The cup that my Father giveth me ſhall I not drink it?</hi> This cup was the moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cup that ever was, or ſhall be mingled; yet the love of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ſufficiently ſweeten it: But the hatred of God doth much more imbitter the afflictions of the wicked, which are of themſelves very bitter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the meaſure of the afflictions of the godly and ungodly, there is likewiſe a very wide difference, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 10. God bids <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> not fear, or be diſmayed. <hi>v.</hi> 11. The reaſon that is rendred, is this, I will correct thee in meaſure. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 27. 8. <hi>In the day of his eaſt-wind, he will ſtay his rough wind.</hi> Although God for his own Glory, and his peoples great good in both worlds, often tries his people to the top of their ſtrength, yet he never did, or will try any of them above their ſtrength. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. <hi>God will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to be tempted above that you are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to bear it.</hi> This is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully comfortable to the people of God, but as for the wicked, God takes no ſuch care about them. If God at any time ſuffer them as it were to ſcramble from under the weight of ſome heavy affliction; before they have well breath'd themſelves, Gods angry hand laies a heavier burden on them, that they cannot ſtand under it, but muſt utterly ſink. God deales with wicked men in this caſe, as enemies in war do; when one enemy hath ſtricken ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther down to the ground, for the preſent he lies like a dead man, and ſtirs neither hand nor foot, and ſo he leaves him, but if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he paſſe by, and obſerve the leaſt ſtirring, he lifts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>up his arm preſently, and fetches an harder blow, and tels him, he will make him that he ſhall never ſtir more: So when God hath made a great breach upon the eſtate, health, or any other comforts of the wicked, for the preſent they are caſt down, but after a while God obſerves they can make a ſorry ſhift to live under thoſe ſtroaks, then God lifts up his angry arm higher the next time, and ſinks
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58289:23"/>
them that they never joy more in any worldly comfort. This is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably illuſtrated by a ſimilitude the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> uſeth, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. ſpeaking of the wicked in time of afflictions, <hi>v.</hi> 18. he ſaith, <hi>The day of the Lord to them is darkneſſe, and not light,</hi> not the leaſt mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of mercy, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. Tis as if one <hi>flee from a Lyon, and a Bear did meet him, or went into the houſe to lean on the wall, and a ſerpent bit him:</hi> Here we ſee the laſt affliction the worſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 20. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſend upon thee curſing, vexation, and rebuke in all that thou ſetteſt thy hand for to do, untill thou be deſtroyed and till thou periſh quickly, becauſe of the wickedneſſe of thy doings whereby thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The difference between the afflictions of the godly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly in the iſſue is as remarkable as any of the former differences. The iſſue of the Saints affliction (as we have already ſhewed is exceeding comfortable in reſpect of the improvement of their graces, and enlargement of their ſpiritual comforts here, and the richer crown of Glory prepared for them in the other world. But as for the wicked mans Afflictions, his corruptions are not purged away, but enraged by them, as the wicked Jewes <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8. 21. In the time of their extreamity they curſed their King, and God; but could ſuch wickedneſſe help them! alas, no, they muſt pay dear for it, <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>They ſhall look unto the earth and behold trouble, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dimneſſe of anguiſh, and they ſhall be driven to darkneſſe:</hi> Still worſe and worſe. A great many wicked perſons that never rightly ſtudied or underſtood either the great evil of ſinne, or ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of divine juſtice, where ſatisfaction cannot be made when they feel painful extremities, uſe to ſay, they hope they have all their hell here; but Chriſts words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 8. may in this caſe fitly be uſed; Their torments here are but the beginnings of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; The wicked in this life do but ſip as it were of the top of the cup of Gods wrath; the bottom, which is the moſt bitter, they muſt be drinking off throughout the eternity of the other world. By this which hath been ſpoken it appears clearly, that the beſt, nay onely way, either to prevent afflictions, or elſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure comfort under them, benefit by them, and infallible delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from them, is to chooſe what holy <hi>Mary</hi> in the Text chooſe <hi>(viz.</hi> the precious wayes of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. Tis true much hath been ſpoken of the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods wayes above all other wayes what ever; But many
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58289:23"/>
a wicked perſon will ſtill object againſt them that ſurely they are not ſo comfortable as hath been aſſerted; becauſe they ſee many who are reputed the holy ones of God, walk (as far as they can diſcern) very ſadly and uncomfortably, from one years end to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; And many that walk in other ways, ſeem as pleaſant and merry at all times as any on earth. Now becauſe one Argument from the Topick of ſence, prevailes with ſenſual unbelievers, more then ten arguments from the Topick of Faith; It will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſpeak ſomething for the Anſwer of this Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solut.</hi> There are two branches of the Objection which muſt be diſtinctly anſwered.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is this; Many Godly ones ſeem very ſad, therefore ſure the ways of God they walk in are not pleaſant. To which I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">I. It muſt not be denied (oh that it could with truth) but that ſome, yea too many precious People of God wrong them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very much, and greatly diſgrace the excellent wayes of God by their uncomfortable walking in them: ſome of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <note place="margin">Horribilia de Deo, terribilia de ſide.</note>much tender pitty, becauſe of the ſad deſertions they are under, and the many fearful temptations they are haunted with from time to time; but as for others of them (were I now at leiſure) it would be a very neceſſary office of love to reprove them ſharply for taking the devils part againſt themſelves, and ſo often rallying together their routed uncomfortable objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own intereſt in the ſure mercies of <hi>David:</hi> But ſure they muſt take another, and better courſe, before their boſoms be filled with the unſpeakable, and glorious joy of the Goſpel. But this being granted, this argues not at all the unpleaſantneſſe of Gods wayes, but onely the failings of ſome that walk in them: And it is the perfection of baſeneſſe for any from hence to take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to reproach the good ways of God, the Doctrine that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſſe, ſtrictly requires all Gods people (and that upon very ſufficient grounds, as you have heard, when I proved they are all the honourable ſpouſes of the King of Glory, and undoubted heirs of the Kingdom of Glory, and ſo have cauſes enough, when they diſcern them immediately; and everlaſtingly to triumph with raviſhing joy) to rejoyce conſtantly and abundantly. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord alway, and I ſay, again rejoyce,</hi> The ingemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here uſed to preſſe the duty notes the difficulty of the duty of ſpirituall rejoycing, and ſo our backwardneſſe to perform it, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58289:24"/>
yet further intimates the exceeding gratefulneſs of it to God when performed. For it is in this caſe expreſſed by God according to the manner of men, when we ſend a child or ſervant to any place for the diſpatch of many buſineſſes; we tell them this, and the other buſineſſe muſt be done, but then ſome one principal thing, on which our heart is ſet, we ſingle out, and tell them, they muſt be ſure, what ever is neglected, to be mindful of that; So here, God would have Chriſtians pray, mourn, and do other holy duties, but he uſeth no ſuch expreſſions about them, pray, yea I ſay, again pray; mourn, yea I ſay, again mourn; But, <hi>Rejoyce, I ſay, again rejoyce:</hi> Becauſe the right performance of this duty is very much according to the heart of God. Ile name but one place more which requires this joy to be enlarged as well as conſtant. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 11. <hi>Be glad in the Lord and rejoyce ye righteous, and ſhout for joy all ye that are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart.</hi> From theſe words we may clearly, and ſtrongly inferre three things, pertinent to our preſent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is vehemently urgent with his people, ſpiritually to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, In the former Text the duty was twice mentioned here it is thrice expreſſed. <hi>Be glad, rejoyce, ſhout for joy.</hi> A beautiful perſon when gracefully ſmiling, appears moſt beautiful; So of all the Chriſtians in the world, none is ſo amiable in the eyes of God as the cheerful Chriſtian, eſpecially when under afflictions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God would have all his people, even the weakeſt of them to rejoyce, for ſo it is expreſſed, <hi>be glad, and rejoyce all ye that are upright in heart;</hi> He doth not ſay all ye that are perfect in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but <hi>all ye that are upright in heart,</hi> although labouring under many ſpiritual infirmities.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God would have this joy to be enlarged; For ſo much is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in thoſe words here uſed, <hi>Shout for joy.</hi> Shouting is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigne of inward and exceſſive joy, ſuch as is the joy of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and of thoſe who divide the ſpoil, which are the greateſt earthly joyes, and to them ſpirituall joys are compared, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. What malicious, and profane villaines are they, who dare call Gods ways uncomfortable, as many do, when they ſee any of Gods people dejected; Oh ſay they, ſuch a preciſe Miniſter hath made ſuch a man or woman mad, he hath undone my wife, or child, tis pitty he ſhould be ſuffered to live; Now if theſe raſh cenſurers would but ask theſe dejected ſouls, why they are thus troubled, they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58289:24"/>
would tell them, It is not the fault of any of thoſe holy Doctrines which Gods faithfull Miniſters deliver, but becauſe they fear they are not at all holy, or at leaſt not ſo holy as they would be, and Gods holy doctrine requires they ſhould be; and ſomtimes it is, becauſe they hear of g orious and raviſhing priviledges, which are the portion of Gods people, and they ſee ſo much ſinfulneſſe, and unworthyneſſe in themſelves, that they dare not lay claim to them, and ſo are tormented upon that account; ſo that things being rightly conſidered, not the holy doctrine delivered by Gods faithful Miniſters, but the unholineſſe of mens hearts, and lives is the true cauſe of their uncomfortableneſſe. And ſo only the ways of ſin, and not the ways of Chriſt deſerve to be branded for unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. But I earneſtly exhort all wicked ones that hear me, to take heed of ſuch groſſe miſtakes, and being ſo greedy to take up and utter ſuch reproaches againſt Gods glorious ways. God will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly reckon with wicked ones for all their hard ſpeeches againſt <note place="margin">Jude 15.</note>him, and then theſe moſt vile, and abhorred words cannot be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Many of the people of God are thought very ſad, when they are very full of inward comfort. The joy of Chriſtians is not a light, frothy, flaſhy, gigling, face mirth, as the joy of the wicked is. <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us, that true joy (even ſuch as he was capable of) is a very ſevere thing: How much more may this be aſſerted of the joy of Chriſtians! Becauſe wicked men ſee the people of God grave and mortified in their countenance, as they ought to be, and not gurning and gigling as themſelves are, they preſently cry out without cauſe; Oh ſad Chriſtians! Oh unpleaſant ways of God! But <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that theſe ſtrangers to Gods ways are not fit judges of them, as to the point of joy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 10. <hi>The heart knowes its own bitterneſse, and a ſtranger doth not intermeddle with his joy.</hi> The wicked know not in what bitterneſſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are ſometimes, ſo as to pitty them, nor yet how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly joyful they are at other times, ſo as thereby to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to get into that comfortable eſtate wherein they live ſo pleaſantly. Further, ſuppoſe thou ſeeſt them often weeping ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they may weep for joy, not for ſorrow, and bitterneſſe of heart; and at other times the cauſe may be not the unpleaſantneſs of the ways of God in which themſelves walk; but the wicked <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 7, 8.</note>and woful ways in which thou, and ſuch as thou art walk, may
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58289:25"/>
make them to abound with tears, as holy <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 136. <hi>Rivers of tears run down mine eyes, becauſe they keep not thy Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Becauſe wicked men are carried ſo much by ſence (bleſſed be God for it) we have enough to ſtop their mouthes from what they may ſee and hear, if they will but obſerve, and remember what they may in this kind; But here their baſeneſſe is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and notoriouſly diſcovered; For they will either not obſerve when they may, or elſe careleſly forget ſuch uſeful obſervations, and inſiſt upon contrary examples. I cannot more fitly compare them for their wickedneſſe to any, then to ſuch (as all the world cries out of) who are idle perſons, who when they come into Tradeſmens ſhops, they deſire to ſee ſome of their wares, ſome is accordingly ſhewed to them, They find fault preſently, offer is made to ſhew them better wares, but they fling away and will not ſee them, which diſcovers plainly their ill minds, who came onely to trouble others by caviling, not to buy any thing for their own uſe; Tis proportionably ſo in this buſineſſe, wicked men pretend a deſire of entring into Gods ways, but that they diſlike the uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable behaviour of ſome who walk in them. Hereupon we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to ſhew them more comfortable Chriſtians; but all this will not prevail to win them to the wayes of God; which is an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſigne, that not the pretended uncomfortableneſſe of ſome Chriſtians, but their own habitual enmity againſt God, and his ways is the true cauſe of their not embracing them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 7. Becauſe <hi>the carnal mind is enmity againſt God; for it is not ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be.</hi> Now for the proof of what is here aſſerted, That there are many (the Lord increaſe their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber daily.) who walk in Gods wayes with much more comfort un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all occurrences, then any other perſons whatever: if wicked ones will but diligently obſerve their own families, and the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of others, they would ſee clearly; That many ſmall loſſes, and croſſes which put them into their dumps, their godly relations and neighbours, do bear with much evenneſſe of ſpirit, and reall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation under the righteous hand of God; and do live much more chearfully in an afflicted eſtate, then they do in a flouriſhing and outwardly proſperous eſtate. They are like <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 4. not only joyful, but exceeding joyful in all their tribulations, which many times wicked men are not, in the greateſt proſperity that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58289:25"/>
they are capable of. So that I may ſay to wicked men, by way of alluſion to <hi>Pauls</hi> words to King <hi>Agrippa, Act.</hi> 26. 27. Do you believe theſe things! I know you do, or at leaſt have cauſe enough to believe them.</p>
            <p>The Second branch of the Objection was, the obſervation of many who walk not in Gods holy and ſtrict wayes, to be alwaies very pleaſant and merry, and therefore their ways are rather to be choſen then Gods ways.</p>
            <p>Beſides what hath been already delivered (which ſome would think abundantly ſufficient to confound this cavil) I ſhall adde Four Conſiderations more, endeavouring (if God be pleaſed to bleſſe them) to make wicked ones aſhamed and afraid of uſing this plea any more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are moſt groundleſſe joys. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>I ſaid of laughter, it is mad, and of mirth what doth it!</hi> It may be truly affirmed of all the joy of the wicked, it is no better then madneſſe. You ſhall come into ſome places, where you meet with thoſe they call naturals, and if you never ſaw, or heard of them before, their exceſſive laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will preſently diſcover them; every word that is ſpoken, and almoſt every ſtraw that is ſtirred puts them into a fit of laughter, as if they were the merryeſt perſons in the whole country; but their friends who ſit and hear it, hang down their pale faces, and ſhed many a bitter tear, under this ſad providence, &amp; would much rather have been childleſſe (if God had ſo pleaſed) then call ſuch a perſon ſon or daughter; They know there is no cauſe for ſuch exceſſive joy, it proceeds wholly from their natural diſtemper; So a great many wicked men, like a company of mad men, laugh, ſhout and revel, as if none in the world ſo merry as they, in the mean time their godly Relations, who know their joys to be wholly ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and proceeding from a ſpirituall phrenſie, weep abundantly in ſecret to ſee them leaping and dancing as it were upon the very borders of the burning lake. God who underſtands their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better then themſelves, tells them (if they dare believe him, and wo to them if they do not) that they have more cauſe to weep: <hi>James</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Go to, now, ye rich men, weep and howl for the miſeries that ſhall come upon you,</hi> (and who beſides God knows how ſoon) wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones live every moment under all the heavy, and dreadful curſes that are written in Gods bleſſed Book. So that for my part, I ſhould judge the condition of many more hopeful, if their laughter
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58289:26"/>
were turned into roaring, and out of a deep ſenſe of their preſent ſinful and dangerous eſtate, they cried out in all companies under the impreſſions of Gods terrours upon them, as the jaylor, <hi>Sirs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 16. 30.</note>
               <hi>what muſt I do to be ſaved!</hi> A through ſence of a preſent bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, is one of the firſt neceſſary ſteps to a better future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are grudged comforts. Godly <hi>Solomon</hi> wiſely adviſeth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 6. <hi>Eat not the bread of him that hath an evil eye, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thou his daintieſt meats.</hi> If it be uncomfortable to partake of the delicates of a Muck-worm's feaſt, who grudgeth what is eaten by his gueſts, how much more may wicked men be unwilling to ſet their hearts upon theſe choiſeſt worldly comforts, which not a churliſh gripple clown, but a gracious, and a bountifull God would not have them to be ſo much delighted with. God ſeemeth to grudge every wicked man every comfortable ſmile he hath while he remaines Chriſtleſſe. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Rejoyce not as other people,</hi> was Gods language by the Prophet, to the unconverted ones to whom he wrote, and ſure he meant as he ſpake. O ye ignorant ſots, that under gray haires underſtand not ſo much of the principles of Religion as a well catechiſed child of ſeven or eight years old. O ye blaſphemous ſwearers, ſwiniſh drunkards, devil-like lyars, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent whores, proud <hi>Jezabels,</hi> greedy Mammoniſts, hypocritical <hi>Judaſes,</hi> and all unregenerate ones of what rank ſoever, in the ruffe of your carnall jollities, remember and ſeriouſly conſider theſe words of the Prophet, and proceed in thoſe abhorred jollities if you dare.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All the joys of the wicked are but ſtolen waters; Tis ſad, yea very ſad living, when a child, or ſervant dwelling in ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward family cannot get a good piece of bread to eat, or any other food, but by ſtealth, when the parents or maſter is in bed and faſt aſleep; Tis ſo with all wicked men, as merry and jovial as they are, were their Conſciences not aſleep for the preſent, we might almoſt as well ſeek, and find joy in hell, as in their boſoms. You that read the ſtory of <hi>Francis Spira,</hi> that will tell you enough to convince you of the utter inconſiſtency of carnal jollity with an awakned and roaring Conſcience: Some of his words were theſe; <hi>Verily De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparation is hell it ſelf: I account my preſent eſtate worſe, then if my ſoul, ſeparated from my body, were with Judas, and therefore I rather deſire to be there, then thus to live in my body.</hi> And no wicked man in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58289:26"/>
the world can be certain that his Conſcience which hath ſlept thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or fourty years, will ſleep one hour, or moment longer; and if it awake, Rejoyce if thou canſt; thy tune and tone then will be nothing but helliſh weeping, and yelling; let thy companions which formerly were moſt pleaſing to thee, come in preſence, then in ſtead of delighting in them, thou wilt be ready to fly in their faces, and to tear out their throats for drawing thee into thoſe ſins, which have brought ſuch an hell into thy woful Conſcience, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 7. We have the Lords words to <hi>Cain, If thou doeſt not well, ſin lies at the door,</hi> there ſin in reſpect of the clamour of guilt in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners conſcience, is compared to a fierce maſtiſfe, or ban-dog, which lies at ſome door, which while it is aſleep, any ſtranger man or child may quietly go in and out the doors; but when the dog awakes, let the ſtouteſt man come near at his utmoſt peril, he barks loudly, and flies greedily at his very throat, and pulls him down, in ſpite of the ſtouteſt reſiſtance he can poſſibly make. <note place="margin">Facti ſunt a corde ſuo fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivi, <hi>Tertul.</hi>
               </note>Now this, and worſe is the caſe of every chriſtleſſe creature, his Conſcience will certainly erelong awake, that is intimated, becauſe you know the noiſe of paſſengers in and out, will not ſuffer a dog to ſleep long at a door, then if it were poſſible every wicked man would run from himſelf, although it were into the midſt of roaring Lyons, greedy Bears, when robbed of their whelps, or ugly and frightfull devils. God then terrifies them with dreams, throws handfuls of hell fire in their faces. An awakned conſcience, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>interpellat cogitantem excitat, dormientem,</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts the ſinner while he is thinking of other things, and awakens him out of his ſleep by ringing that doleful peal in his ears, that makes him ſtart and ſtare, <hi>Veni miſer in judicium,</hi> Come thou wretch and receive thy judgement for all theſe baſe and God-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking abominations.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To name no more at this time. All the joyes of the wicked are very coſtly, yea over coſtly joyes. We ſay of the beſt gold, it may be bought to dear; tis certainly ſo in referrence to all the comforts of the wicked in ſinful waies: let them be fancied to be never ſo ſweet, I am ſure their price is too great. The loſſe of heavens unconceivable joyes, and the ſence of hels unimaginable miſeries to all eternity, is the price of the ſorry, ſenſuall, bruitiſh delights in this world: between the price and purchaſed joys of worldlings, becauſe the price is infinite, and the joy purchaſed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58289:27"/>
is finite, There can be no proportion: There is no queſtion, but many wicked men dream golden dreams, as if they might merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dance all their dayes after the Devils pipe, and ſup with Chriſt in glory. But the conceit is ſo groſſe, that the very naming of it ſeems a ſufficient confutation: I muſt now in Gods name ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beſeech wicked ones wel to weigh the words of his dear Son, recorded <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 25. <hi>Wo be to you that now laugh, for ye ſhall mourn and weep.</hi> One would think, that if Chriſt had onely ſaid <hi>mourn,</hi> or <hi>weep,</hi> it had been ſufficient, but he ſaith, <hi>mourn and weep,</hi> that is abundantly mourn, and mourn, and do nothing elſe but mourn. A wicked mans joy is like a book fairly bound, which when it is opened is full of nothing but mournful Tragedies: But this is not all; becauſe the Scripture is its own beſt interpreter, I muſt by warrant of another Scripture tell wicked men, that at the time of execution of Gods fearfull vengeance upon them, he will proportion the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his flaming wrath then, to the meaſure of their ſinful jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, in the dayes of their provocation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 7. God tells us how he will deal with wicked <hi>Babylon,</hi> and conſequently with all other Chriſtleſſe ſinners in the day of his wrath; how much ſhe hath glorified her ſelf, and lived deliciouſly, ſo much torment, and ſorrow give her; For ſhe ſaith in her heart, <hi>I ſit as a Queen and ſhall ſee no ſorrow;</hi> When God ſhall reckon with men in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, how unconceivably fearfull above others will their condition be, who while they lived here, being as the Apoſtle <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3: 4.</note>ſpeaks, <hi>lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God,</hi> ſpent all that time (which ſhould have been employed in ſerving and glorifying God, in examining their deceitfull hearts, weeping over their rebellions againſt God, praying fervently for the pardon of them, and power againſt them) in bowling, and hunting, hawking, or which is worſe, unlawfully gaming, immoderately drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whoring, and the like prodigious practiſes, and the more ſinful mirth any day, the better they judged that time to be ſpent; But when God ſhall ſay to them in the day of his wrath according to his own words above mentioned, ſo much as theſe wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have lived deliciouſly, ſo much ſorrow and torment ſhall be given to them; Oh then when it is too late wicked ones may wiſh, Oh that I had never been in any ſuch merry company all my daies. If I had been leſſe joyful, then ſhould I have been leſſe miſerable to all eternity; the pleaſures of ſin were but for a ſhort ſeaſon, thy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58289:27"/>
vengeance will be eternal. Oh moſt woful purchaſe made by a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſelf-conceited, and ſelf-deluded ſinner, that would take no warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, either from the Preachers in their Pulpits, or Conſcience the Preacher in their boſoms. The good Lord grant that theſe and the like Conſiderations may take off ſome poor ſoules from their greedineſſe after the Devils cup of ſweet poyſon.</p>
            <p>This for the explication, confirmation, and vindication of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt thing promiſed is the Application of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Of Information.</p>
            <p>This being ſo, as we have heard, That the Choice of the truly godly perſon is unqueſtionably, and incomparably the beſt choice which can be made: Many things might be collected by way of Information. I ſhall note onely one.</p>
            <p>Hereby we are informed that the truly godly perſons are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably the wiſeſt perſons in the world, becauſe their choice is the beſt choice: For in nothing more clearly doth the wiſdom or folly of men, and women appear, then in the choices which are made by them. A good Choice argues wiſdom, and a bad one folly. And therefore God when as he doth uſually brand wicked ones, (who are fondly conceited of themſelves, as if they were the onely wiſe perſons in the world) with the mark of folly, uſeth ſuch an Argument as is taken from their bad choice to prove it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>How long ye ſimple ones will ye love ſimplicity, and ye ſcorners delight in ſcorning, and fools hate knowledge.</hi> Amongſt other Arguments, God uſeth to prove theſe wicked ones to be fools, and ſimple ones, this is one, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29. <hi>They did not chooſe the fear of the Lord.</hi> To preferre counters above gold, pebbles above pearls, can proceed from nothing but childiſh ignorance, and notorious ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity: And yet ſo bad, or rather much worſe is their choice, who prefer carnall comforts before ſpiritual, and temporal before eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal bleſſings, as all the wicked ones in the world do. Wicked ones think the Lords people a company of ſilly perſons, becauſe they <hi>run not with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot:</hi> but <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 4.</note>the Lords people know that they are guilty of the greateſt folly imaginable, as God (who is beſt able to judge) hath often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in his Word. On the o her hand, the onely wiſe God cals all godly ones the children of wiſdome, <hi>Matthew,</hi> 11. 19.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58289:28"/>
And ſeeing the wiſdome of Heaven pronounceth them wiſe, they need not regard the contrary judgement of the worlds profane and proud ſots, who are as blind as beetles in Gods matters, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though eagle-ey'd in worldly affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> 
               <note place="margin">Of Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> If the Godly perſons choice be the beſt; Let the conſideration of this Doctrine prevail with us to make diligent enquiry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have made this choice as yet, or not? This trial might be managed by propounding to our ſelves ſuch Queſtions as are ſuitable to the ſeveral branches of the deſcription of the Godly mans choice, mentioned in the explication of the Doctrine; as namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether God hath wrought a great change in us by the infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſupernatural and ſpecial Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What reſpect our ſouls bear to the Ordinances of Grace, and in ſeveral other particulars: But to paſſe by them, I will briefly touch upon this one other general Note.</p>
            <p>If we have choſen God, and the waies of God, it will infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly appear by the delight which we take both in himſelf and them; for whatſoever is choſen by us is ever delightful to us. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 30. compared with <hi>v.</hi> 35. Now this delight manifeſts it ſelf after this manner:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By our engaging in the precious waies of God without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay; So it was with holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119. 30. <hi>I have choſen the way of truth;</hi> how did that appear? <hi>V.</hi> 60. <hi>I made haſte, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed not to keep thy Commandments.</hi> By this note of trial, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears thoſe that put off God and his work (as moſt do) from one week, moneth, nay, year unto another, have no delight in the waies of God, and conſequently have not made the choice of the Text.</p>
            <p>We do not hear men ſay, and tell God, that they will not at all believe in Chriſt, repent of their ſins, and yield obedience to his holy Commandments; but they have no mind to ſet upon theſe and other ſpiritual duties preſently. Some thing or other ſtill comes in the way to cauſe procraſtination: Some worldly bargain muſt be carried through, ſome recreation muſt be followed, ſome graceleſſe company attended, ſome luſt ſatisfied, before they can find leiſure to work the work of God. Such a deluded ſinner is ſpoken of, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 28, 30. <hi>Son, Go work to day in my Vineyard.</hi> This is Gods voice to all that chooſe him, and his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58289:28"/>
waies, without delay to engage in them. Not ſo much as one day more is allowed by God for ſinful practiſes. <hi>V.</hi> 30. The graceleſſe ſinner anſwers, as if he intended to comply with the voice of God; But the time was not yet come; he ſaid, <hi>I go, Sir,</hi> but went not. It was a wiſe Obſervation of <hi>Seneca; Stultus ſemper incipit vivere;</hi> and elſewhere ſpeaking of ſuch, ſaith, <hi>Semper victuri,</hi> they are alwaies about to live better, but never begin. So <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his time made a like Obſervation, <hi>Modo, &amp; modo, non habent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> the heartleſſe eſſays and hypocritical purpoſes of ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners come to nothing. How many when they are ſick, and fear death, and ſo can enjoy the riches of the world, delights of the fleſh, and pleaſures of ſin no longer, complement with God, and as if they were raviſhed with the beauty of his waies, make libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall promiſes, as if for time to come, they would never walk in any other paths but Gods; but, alas, common experience makes it evident (if God ſpare them) that they were no true-hearted Chriſtians, but as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 22. <hi>Dogs return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their vomit.</hi> A dog that loves ſtinking carrion above other things, yet when the cudgel is over his head, forbeareth: So when the King of terrours ſtands over theſe perſons, they keep out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly at a diſtance from ſin; but afterwards they are ſo much the more greedy of wicked company, and waies, becauſe of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reſtraint.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trial</hi> 2. Gen. 25. 29.</note> We are not ſo apt to be weary of thoſe things wherein we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light as in other things. Take a carnal man that is addicted to Hunting, he will run many miles in a day, that a ſtranger, who obſerves it, wonders, he is able after ſo much travel to ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his legs, that he doth not preſently drop down upon the ground like a fainting man: Let the ſame man be required to go one quarter of the way to the place of Gods worſhip, he will tell you 'tis impoſſible for him to walk half ſo far, his ſtrength will not bear it, and God will have mercy, and not ſacrifice. Now the reaſon of this difference is clearly this, his delight in Hunting prevents his wearineſſe in that exerciſe, but his want of delight in Gods worſhip, cauſeth his wearineſſe in a far leſſer walk. I might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly multiply pregnant inſtances of the unwearied diligence of thoſe who have choſen the waies of God. <hi>Davids</hi> example is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable to this purpoſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 147. <hi>I prevented the dawning of the morning, and cryed,</hi> Pſal. 55. 17. <hi>Evening, and morning and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58289:29"/>
at noon will I pray, and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my voice.</hi> Pſalm 119. 62. <hi>At midnight will I ariſe, and give thanks.</hi> This good man, who had choſen and delighted in Gods waies, is at Gods work early and late, and the day will not ſerve his turn, but at midnight he awakes for the worſhip of God; but now on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, many who are angry, if you do not admire them for rare Chriſtians, yet it may be ſaid of them as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in another caſe, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>The ſhew of their countenance doth witneſſe againſt them.</hi> Their faces are ſo different in different pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as if they were not the ſame men: in their own houſes, and in their Market-places, and Fairs, they look as cheerfully, and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly, as any in the world: but in Gods houſe where his holy Ordinances are attended, they look ſo drowzily, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentedly, and ſadly, as if they were a company of ſick or dying men. This was the temper of thoſe ſinners mentioned, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 13. who cryed out againſt the worſhip of God: <hi>Behold, what a wearineſſe it is,</hi> and they ſnuffed at it: No day with them ſo long as the Sabbath, no hours ſo long as thoſe that are ſpent in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God. This accurſed ſpirit was in thoſe we read of, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 5. <hi>When will the Sabbath be over, that we may ſet forth wheat,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trial</hi> 3.</note> What is done with delight, is done very frequently. The Swi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Drunkard doth not ſatisfie himſelf once or twice in a year to go to the Ale-houſe, but becauſe he delighteth in drunken company, he goeth often to ſuch places. The unclean perſon doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 8.</note>himſelf to walk once or twice in a year to a Whore-houſe; but his <hi>Munday, Tueſday,</hi> I had almoſt ſaid, his every daies walk is towards the Whores corner. 'Tis proportionably ſo in ſpiritual matters. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>They that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another.</hi> The Saints delight in mutual Conferences, and manifeſt their delight by being frequent in their communion one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The devotion of one, who hath choſen the waies of God, is not like the condition of one that hath an Ague, ſometimes ſick, and ſometimes well; one day for God, and another for the world, and the Devil. <hi>David</hi> who delighted in the waies of God, could ſay with confidence before the Searcher of hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 20. <hi>My ſoul breaketh for the longing it hath to thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at all times.</hi> And indeed the waies of God being alway the ſame, that which draws forth your delight at one time, may
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58289:29"/>
be found to engage your hearts to them at all times; they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beautiful, and equally beautiful; they are alwaies pleaſing to God, and means of precious communion with God. And therefore whoever ſeem religious only by fits and in certain good moods, as they call them, cannot give good proof, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the waies of God: nor can the ſoul of God delight in ſuch hypocrites. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 4. We may obſerve Gods diſlike of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy. <hi>Oh</hi> Ephraim, <hi>What ſhall I do unto thee! Oh</hi> Judah, <hi>What ſhall I do unto thee, for your goodneſſe is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it paſſeth away:</hi> as if God had ſaid, Oh <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> Oh <hi>Judah,</hi> I know not what to do with you. Thy doing good only by fits, and good moods is juſtly abhorring to men, but much more abominable in the ſight of God. What Father, or Maſter can brook that ſon or ſervant, that will happily do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is required of them, but not conſtantly. Certainly ſuch as are not conſtant in the waies of God, delight not in them, and he cannot with honour accept of ſuch unconſtant ſervices, wherein his Authority is ſo palpably neglected and contemned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trial</hi> 4.</note> What is undertaken with delight, is carried on with reſolution, and impatiency of oppoſition: Many a man froward enough in his ſpirit, will ſuffer himſelf in many ſmaller things to be croſſed; but if he be oppoſed in his darling deſign, you may almoſt as ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encounter a Bear robbed of her whelps. This is evident in the example of holy <hi>David.</hi> We read in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 30. He had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the way of truth, which was the way of God. <hi>V.</hi> 106. His reſolution to carry on that work of God is eminently expreſſed; <hi>I have ſworn, and will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous judgements.</hi> One that hath choſen the way of God, may by the violence of ſome ſtrong temptation, be juſtled out of the holy path for a ſhort ſpace of time; but when he can recover himſelf from that violence, he returns with as great, yea greater zeal then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly into Wiſdomes pleaſant waies: The ſweeteſt bait, nay, all the pleaſant baits, that Satan can uſe at one time are not bribe big enough to make the true Chriſtian to forſake the waies of God, which he hath once choſen. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 24. By faith <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he was come to years refuſed to be called the ſon of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter; chuſing rather to ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon. Pleaſure, riches, and honour are the Summer of the worlds alluring benefits; yet holy
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58289:30"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> gallantly turns his back upon them all, and ſaw more ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe in Gods waies, although under the moſt diſcouraging appearance, in a time of greateſt affliction; then in the waies of ſin, when in the moſt tempting garb of proſperity in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court. The ſpeech of <hi>Galeacius Caracciola,</hi> the Noble Marqueſſe of <hi>Vico,</hi> was very remarkable to this purpoſe, when he was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted with a very great ſumme of money to forſake his Religion, he manifeſted his holy indignation againſt ſuch a baſe proffer, in theſe words: Let your money periſh with you, who eſteem all the gold in the world worth one daies communion with Jeſus Chriſt: and as they cannot be bribed out of the waies of God; ſo neither can the worlds greateſt affrightments ſcare them from Chriſts ſervice. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. We read of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> dedicating a Golden Image in <hi>Dura,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 14. tells <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> that if they would not worſhip it, they ſhould be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the midſt of a burning fiery Furnace. <hi>V.</hi> 16, 17, 18. you may read their ſtout and gallant anſwer. <hi>We are not careful to anſwer thee in this matter:</hi> as if they had ſaid, Go, Scare children with thy great words; our God can deliver us, if he pleaſe, but if not, ſuppoſe the worſt, we are at a point, we are reſolved not to fall off from Gods ſervice to ſuch abhorred worſhip. A great many ſeem to have choſen the waies of God, and follow the chaſe hard, till they meet with honey, (as it is in the Story, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.) but then <hi>Demas</hi>-like they forſake their duty, embracing the preſent world, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. And others, who do not thus miſcarry, are through inordinate fear of worldly troubles, and diſadvantages, hindred from an holy courſe; like thoſe unſound Profeſſours of Religion, repreſented by the ſtony ground, who when trouble and perſecution for the Goſpels ſake did ariſe, were immediately offended, <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 17. In ſhort, by what hath been ſaid, the palpable difference between thoſe who have, and thoſe who have not choſen the waies of God, is evident; Neither worldly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, nor fear can take off Gods people from his waies which they have choſen: but as for others, if the honey of worldly pleaſures, profits, or preferment doth not corrupt them, and ſtop them from embracing, and proceeding in an holy courſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the frown of a rich Kinſman, or Landlord, the ſcoffs of profane neighbors, or the ſight of a ſtake of Martyrdom, will certainly keep them to their dying day in the Tabernacles and courſes of the ungodly. I have now
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58289:30"/>
diſpatcht ſome brief Notes of Trial, by which they who are not willing to put a cheat upon their ſouls, may by the bleſſing of God make a true diſcovery of their choice, whether it be good, or bad, ſafe, or damnable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> If the choice of Godly Ones be unqueſtionably, and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably the beſt choice which can be made. This Doctrine calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to take up a moſt bitter Lamentation upon this great Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that there are ſo very few that make this choice: The paucity of thoſe who make this choice will be readily acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe, who obſerve the behaviour of the greateſt part of men and women, and compare the ſame with what hath been before ſpoken touching the diſcovery of a right choice. None that chooſe Gods pleaſant waies, but manifeſt their delight in them; as there are abundance of unanſwerable grounds for ſuch an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards them: But, alas, to that height of prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods waies, are the generality of people riſen, that if you invite them into Gods pleaſant waies, they are ready to tell you to your faces, you invite them to their loſſe; as if in the worlds <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 17.</note>wilderneſſe more delight might juſtly be expected, then in the true Paradiſe of Chriſtianity; as if <hi>Aegypts</hi> Onions and Garlick were more refreſhing, then <hi>Canaans</hi> Grapes. And the great ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of this folly appears when we conſider, what ſorry and pitiful things they are which hinder this incomparable choice: all which may be fitly reduced to theſe 3 heads: 1. The brutiſh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. 2. The deceitful riches. 3. The empty honours of this vain world. Well, I dare not enter into this large Field, but ſhut up this diſcourſe with thoſe words of the Prophet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19. 14. <hi>This is a Lamentation, and ſhall be for a Lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt Uſe which I ſhall a little inſiſt upon is by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in two branches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is the Godly perſons choice unqueſtionably, and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably the beſt choice which can be made. Then me thinks, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, I may addreſſe an Exhortation to all of you, that hear me this day, who have not yet made this choice, 1. To alter your choice, and be ſatisfied with no choice, but the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent one, which this Doctrine holds forth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this choice be the beſt, it cannot be made too ſoon; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay not to follow the counſel of this Exhortation, the ſooner it is made the better.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58289:31"/>
I begin with the firſt branch of the Exhortation, for the preſſing whereof almoſt innumerable Arguments offer themſelves for its enforcement. For what is the ſcope of the whole Bible, but to take off men from that baſe choice, which all naturally make, and to engage them to make ſuch a choice, as Godly <hi>Mary</hi> in the Text made. I have leiſure only to hint a very few Arguments to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And many of the moſt excellent Arguments I muſt for their largeneſſe omit, as namely, the admirable pleaſantneſſe of the waies of God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Her waies are waies of pleaſantneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. 2. The eaſineſſe of the waies of God if compared with the worlds drudgery, and Satans ſlavery in the waies of ſin, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 29, 30. But the explication, confirmation, and vindication of theſe, and ſuch like Arguments from the cavils of graceleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to whom they are the greateſt Paradoxes in the world, would require rather a large Volumn then a ſmal part of a ſingle Sermon.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore take up ſome few other Arguments of quicker diſpatch: And one would think much might be ſaid in a few words, that may be very perſwaſive for this choice I have been ſpeaking of. But I remember the ſtory of one, who after his Converſion ſeemed to think that the evidence of Gods Arguments to bring off from ſin to Chriſt, was ſuch, that ſcarce any that conſidered them could withſtand the ſtrength of them; but by much ſad experience he afterwards found, that old <hi>Adam</hi> was too hard for young <hi>Melancthon.</hi> However the great God, who can perſwade, deals with men as reaſonable creatures, and offers <note place="margin">Hoſ. 11. 4.</note>Arguments to move them to a compliance with himſelf. I ſhall therefore produce ſome few of his Arguments, praying, and hoping for his good bleſſing to make them effectual.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> 1. If God and the things of God be not choſen by us, we ſhall never enjoy him, and then farewell all true happineſſe for ever. 'Tis an amazing wonder of merciful condeſcention, that God at our firſt Creation ſhould ſo highly honour duſt and aſhes, as to afford them communion with himſelf, and thereby glorious hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: but after mankind had wilfully turn'd the back upon God, for him (who paſſed by all the faln Angels, who were in the higheſt rank of creatures) to court rebellious duſt and aſhes to return, and accept of happineſſe in a renewed communion with his heavenly Highneſſe through Chriſt as our Mediatour. This is <note place="margin">2 Per. 1. 12.</note>that great myſtery, which the Angels willingly pry into, as if
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58289:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Heaven it ſelf could not furniſh them with an object more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of admiration; And yet notwithſtanding this moſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> prono capite &amp; propenſo collo accurate intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicire.</note>willingneſſe of God to beſtow himſelf upon the children of men for their happineſſe (for he himſelf hath no need of them) yet the Scripture giveth us clear aſſurance, that none ſhall enjoy him who are finally ſo graceleſſe as not to chooſe him. This was well obſerved by holy and learned <hi>Auſtin</hi> long ſince, <hi>Qui fecit te ſine te non ſervabit te ſine te,</hi> He that made thee without thee, will not ſave thee without thee; that is, he will not force himſelf and ſalvation upon any in a ſtrange prodigality againſt their wills. This account we have given from God himſelf by the hand of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> Prov. 1. 26, 27, 28. God ſpeaking of the certain and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſolation of the wicked, notwithſtanding their ſuppoſed ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſuit for ſalvation, alledges this reaſon for it, <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>they did not chooſe the fear of the Lord;</hi> and therefore (as they well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) God was reſolved to withhold ſalvation from them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>If we take up with any thing on this ſide God, and the things of God in our choice, we are not ſure, if we were the greateſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of worldly wiſdome that can be found on earth, to obtain what we make choice of. Art thou a fond admirer of a great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and thereupon doſt bend all thy wits to compaſſe it, ſparing no pains in the ſeeking riches; when thou haſt uſed thy utmoſt skill and diligence to get a great eſtate, in ſpight of thy heart thou maiſt dye under Beggars buſh. This <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved in his time (and any wiſe man may make the like obſervation in our time) <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 11. <hi>Riches are not alwaies to men of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Deut. 8. 18. <hi>It is God that giveth power to whom he pleaſe to get wealth.</hi> And it might be added by the warrant of other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to keep it, when they have got it. Again, doth thy ſoul thirſt after the favour of great ones! without the help of God this can never be compaſſed by the greateſt wiſdome and diligence that any ambitious perſon can poſſibly uſe. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 11. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>That favour is not to men of skill.</hi> They who are moſt skilful to diſcover the temper, and accordingly to humour thoſe whoſe favour they are greedy of, are moſt probable to obtain their favour, but be they never ſo skilful, they often miſſe their mark. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. Promotion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; but God is the Judge, he putteth down one, and ſetteth up another. The hearts of all are in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58289:32"/>
Gods hands, and it is he alone that can incline them towards us, or turn them from us. Now what hath been ſaid concerning mans inability to obtain worldly wealth, or favour, may as truly be aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted concerning al other temporal good things whatſoever. Now this being ſo, let us learn wiſdome from the ſad experience of others diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments, who miſplace their choice, to chooſe that which is moſt worthy our choice, and moſt certain to be enjoyed if cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, <hi>(viz.)</hi> an intereſt in Gods favour with all the glorious benefits of both worlds that flow from it; whereas if we chooſe other things of leſſe worth, it will be our ſad lot to fare as thoſe who affect marriages with thoſe above their rank, or unwilling other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to comply with them, they fret and grieve themſelves into deadly conſumptions, and leave their names behind them under the ſevere cenſures of obſerves, for their notorious weakneſſe and proud folly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> Suppoſe God ſhould ſuffer ſome few worldlings to obtain thoſe worldly comforts that they have choſen, and all their days hunted after with hotteſt chaſe imaginable, although the things they obtain are in themſelves the good and comfortable bleſſings of God; they may be as far from ſuch happineſſe as ſuch things are capable of affording, as they were before. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>I know that there is no good in them,</hi> that is, the things of this world, <hi>but for a man to rejoice, and to do good in his life; and alſo that every man ſhould eat and drink, and enjoy the good of all his labour, it is the gift of God;</hi> and if ſo, then not in the power of any one in the world without the help and bleſſing of God. What is a rich mans condition better then a poor mans, if he do not uſe it, do good with it, and take comfort in it? But this is manifeſt by common experience, that many ſuch perſons have as little or leſſe comfort of their eſtates then thoſe who have not the hundredth part of ſuch an eſtate: and the like may be ſaid of all worldly bleſſings. One cannot chooſe but ſtand and wonder, what ſome perſons ail to look ſo ſadly, and live ſo diſcontentedly as they do from one years end to another; when if we obſerve their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly portion, one can ſcarce find any pleaſant thing that God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds from them; many times 'tis only the want of ſome ſmall matter, that their extravagant fancies fix upon, which is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable in it ſelf, that they are aſhamed to own it as the ground of their diſſatifaction with their condition. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58289:32"/>
4, 6. <hi>Ahab</hi> ſeems as if he would make a dye of it, ſurely ſome great matter is the cauſe of it; but the ſtory tells us, it was only becauſe <hi>Naboth</hi> denied him his little Vineyard, when himſelf (as is probable) had more and far better of his own. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> upon this place cites an Epiſtle of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to a friend of his, in which he makes a compariſon between <hi>Naboth</hi> and <hi>Ahab,</hi> and pronounceth poor <hi>Naboth</hi> in a better condition then rich <hi>Ahab,</hi> becauſe he was comfortable in the enjoyment of his little, and <hi>Ahab</hi> ſinfully and ſottiſhly diſcontented notwithſtanding his great abundance. A great many ſtrangely fancy, that if they could but ſcrue up their eſtates to ſuch an height as they propound to themſelves, or get into the favour of ſome that are great in the world, none in the world ſhould live more comfortably then themſelves: but alas, many times they weare out their bodies, ſtretch and torment their conſciences, and cannot be maſters of their deſigns; and if at any time they obtain what they eagerly ſeek, they never meet with one half or hundred part of comfort in ſuch a condition as they promiſed to themſelves. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſeriouſly offer to their conſideration that Scripture, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>He that loveth ſilver ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver, and he that loveth abundance, with encreaſe; this alſo is vanity.</hi> The like is true of all worldly enjoyments: And therefore if God tels worldly men, that they ſhall never obtain comfortable ſatisfaction in their greateſt abundance, it is the vaineſt thing in the world for them to think to prove God a Lyar, which is black blaſphemy in the leaſt to imagine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> If thou makeſt any other choice, it will certainly provoke the fearful and juſt indignation of Jeſus Chriſt againſt thee. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 14. Chriſt ſpeaking of the recompence of the righteous at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, one who ſits by cries out by way of admiration. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>Bleſſed are they who ſhall eat bread in the Kingdom of God:</hi> As if he had ſaid in other words, I chooſe the happy condition of Chriſts people above all things in the world beſides. But Chriſt preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the diſcovering of his unſoundneſſe propounds the Parable of the Gueſts, who were invited to partake of thoſe things he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to admire and chooſe, and then we read, <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19, 20. that all made their excuſes, (as if they would not go to Hell without ſome ſeeming good reaſons) One had a great Farm to look after, another a new bargain, a third a wife; all which they preferred
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58289:33"/>
before the things of Chriſts Kingdom. Well, how did Chriſt take this at their hands? I anſwer, His indignation flamed out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. <hi>V.</hi> 21. We read he was angry, and if you deſire to know how great his anger was, <hi>v.</hi> 24. it is ſaid, The perſons who preferred the things of this world before the things of his Kingdom, ſhould not taſte of his Supper, that is, ſhould not partake of the leaſt degree of his comfortable favour, which was the ſpiritual delicacy of that great Supper. As if Chriſt had ſaid in the height of his indignation, I will never vouchſafe ſuch a wretch ſo much as one loving look in this, or the other world. And here by the way, let worldlings take notice, that the perſons mentioned in the Parable preferred lawful worldly comforts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comforts of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> their Farms, bargains, and wives. A great many think if the things they ſet their hearts upon be lawful, there is no danger of inordinacy; but we ſee this Scripture ſpeaks the contrary. With what face can any ſtand before Chriſt at the laſt great and terrible day, and ſay, Lord, I preferred the ſenſual pleaſures of Hunting, Hawking, Bowling, and other worldly pleaſures, which are but for a ſeaſon, before <note place="margin">Pſal. 116. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note>the pleaſures of thy Kingdom, and right hand, which are for evermore. According to the judgement of right reaſon, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual pleaſures are much better then ſenſual, which gratifie our brutiſh part; and there is no compariſon between comforts that are only for a ſeaſon, (as all the comforts of this world are) and the comforts of the other world which are eternal. In ſhort, by preferring any worldly comfort before Chriſt, and the things of Chriſt, thou doſt as it were ſay, My money is better then Chriſt, the favour of a rich Feprobate is better then the favour of the eternal God, and the alone All-ſufficient Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Now this great diſgrace and reproach, Jeſus Chriſt, as you have heard, will never bear at the hands of ſottiſh ſinners. But then where ſhall theſe Monſters appear with comfort? who ſay the pleaſures of ſin are better then the pleaſures of godlineſſe, that prefer the ſmiles and favour of a filthy Whore, before the favour of Jeſus Chriſt; that ſay, the wine on earth is better then the new wine prepared in the Kingdom of God. If Chriſt be juſtly enraged againſt thoſe who prefer Earth before Heaven, he cannot but be much more incenſed againſt thoſe who prefer Hell before Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58289:33"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>5</label> The certain iſſue of any other choice will be wofull. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who in this, as in other things, manifeſts himſelf to be a liar, ſuggeſts to ſinners that God is ſo merciful, &amp; pittiful to his creatures, that he cannot find in his heart to pour ſo much burning indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon them as he hath threatned againſt them in his word, and therefore they need not abridge themſelves of the pleaſure of their darling iniquities, this was the prevailing temptation, by which our firſt parents were deluded. God threatned <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17. cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain death if they did eat of the forbidden fruit, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 4. Satan ſuggeſts the contrary. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſurely die.</hi> We know by ſad experience the truth of Gods commination, and the falſhood of Satans inſinuation; learn therefore, O ye ſons, and daughters of men to believe God, and not Satan, God tels us plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that if we chooſe the ways of ſinne, we cannot avoid the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith concerning one way of ſin is true of every way of ſinne, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Her feet go down to death her ſteps take hold of hell.</hi> Amongſt other pregnant Scriptures to prove the certain iſſue of a bad choice, thoſe remarkable words of the Pſalmiſt are conſiderable, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11. 6. <hi>Upon the wicked he will rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible tempeſt, this ſhall be the portion of their cup.</hi> No man living is able fully to conceive, and expreſſe how much wofull miſery is implied in theſe expreſſions. <note place="margin">Nah. 1. 6. Rev. 21. 8.</note>With men the torments cauſed by fire are judged rightly amongſt the greateſt of torments; and therefore God uſeth often this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor, to ſet out the miſerable condition that ſhall befal the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both worlds: But that is not all, fire alone cauſeth exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite torments, but fire and brimſtone together, cauſe a much fiercer flame. And this fire is not ſaid to be dropt, which notes, a ſmall quantity, but to be poured down, which intimates a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his wrath, that ſhall fall upon the wicked: And yet further it is obſervable, that this great meaſure of wrath ſhall not come down upon the wicked leiſurely, and calmely, but like rain in a mighty tempeſt, one drop haſtily after the other with abundance of terrible violence. It is ſaid here, that it ſhall be an horrible tempeſt of fire, that ſhall deſcend upon the wicked. God will not come to the dying beds of Chriſtleſſe ſinners, and ſay, tell me ye abhorred drunkards, ſwearers, lyars, cheaters, and all ye unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate perſons of what name ſoever, are ye willing to be damned! you have choſen and walked in the ways of ſinne which lead to hell,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58289:34"/>
and all the threatnings and promiſes of my bleſſed book, could not ſtop you in your ſinful courſe! Are you willing to enter into the gates of darkneſſe, and to be priſoners in hell for ever! But I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of your Anſwer if ſuch Queſtions were propounded; Oh no, dear God of mercy, we cannot bear the thoughts of ſuch a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The wicked will be ready then to uſe thoſe words of the Prophet, before cited, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 14. <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with devouring fire! Who ſhall endure everlaſting burnings!</hi> A great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſimple perſons, think, that when people being horribly afraid of everlaſting burnings, cry earneſtly to God to be delivered from that fearful miſery, they are certainly penitent, and that God cannot find in his heart to damn them: But alas, the devil in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed perſon had as much grace as this comes to, <hi>Mark.</hi> 5. 6. It is ſaid, <hi>he worſhipped,</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. the words which he uſed, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded: <hi>I adjure thee by God, that thou torment me not:</hi> But no ſuch language will prevail with Chriſt to releaſe Devils from everlaſting torments, nor will like words be effectual for the keeping any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally unregenerate from the damnation of hell. Wicked men here by their ſinnes croſſe Gods revealed will, and God is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the other world to croſſe their wills, by inflicting intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable puniſhments upon them for thoſe ſins. And therefore Gods language in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11. 6. is peremptory without any perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, This ſhall be their portion, will they, nill they, and ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 46. <hi>Theſe ſhall go into everlaſting puniſhment.</hi> Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinners now grieve Gods ſpirit bere by their rebellions, and God is fully reſolved to make all the veines of their heart to ake to all eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>6</label> The moſt wiſe and pittiful God will laugh at the folly of thoſe who make any other choice then that which is here commended in this Text. It is a very bitter aggravation of the ſad condition of a Malefactor, when he is going to execution, to ſee a company of people about him to clap their hands, laugh and ſhout for joy, to ſee him carried to the place of execution, to hear them talking one to another, here goes a fool, that muſt dy like a dog in a ſtring, becauſe for a little money he hath forfeited his life to juſtice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his name and friends to a laſting reproach, and his whole ſelf to the danger of everlaſting miſery in the other world. At ſuch times the children of men ſhould be of better behaviour, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying and praying for the woful ſinner, and bleſſing the name of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58289:34"/>
God for keeping them (as prone as others) from falling into ſuch reproachful, and dangerous miſcarriages; But if it be ſo bitter, when under miſery, to want the compaſſion of fooliſh and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted men, tis abundantly more miſerable, under far greater miſery to be reproached, but not pittyed by him who is a God of infinite wiſdome, and moſt tender compaſſion. That this fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſad condition will befal the wicked, is evident from thoſe words of God by <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>How long ye ſimple ones will ye love ſimplicity, and ye ſcorners delight in ſcorning, and fools hate knowledge? Becauſe I have called and ye have refuſed, I have ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out my hands and none regarded; but ye have ſet at nought all my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and would none of my reproof: I alſo will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your fear cometh. When your fear cometh as deſolation, and your deſtruction cometh as a whirlwind, when diſtreſſe and anguiſh cometh upon you. Then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeek me early but ſhall not find me; for that they hated know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and did not chooſe the fear of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When ſinners are weeping, yelling, and gnaſhing their teeth under Gods fearful vengeance, and they calling aloud for favour, and God regards their cry no more, then men regard the howling of beaſts and barking of dogs; but laughs in their faces, as it were and mocks them, telling them, they were ſimple ones, and ſtark fools, who for the pleaſures of ſinne, which laſt, and they knew would laſt but for a ſeaſon, they wilfully expoſed themſelves to that fearfull indignation of God; which they were often aſſured would be intollerable and everlaſting. One would wonder with what face any ſuch ſinner can look upon God and beg his mercy, when God may ſuddenly put them to ſilence by telling them, he damnes none but thoſe, who chooſe damnation, and how can they reaſonably except againſt their own choice. I eaſily imagine what will be pleaded by ſinners in this caſe; They never did, nor can any chooſe ſuch miſery for their portion, nothing is more abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to their thoughts. That which is the Object of the Wills choice, muſt be preſented under the form and notion of good to the creature: But this appears to them in that form which is moſt contrary to the creatures good and welfare. Well, Let ſinners pleaſe themſelves never ſo much with ſuch ſeemingly learned Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections; God will quickly out-argue them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. God by <hi>Moſes</hi> calls upon the people to walk in the way of holy obedience
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58289:35"/>
to all his commandments, and not to dare to diſobey any of them, and backs his exhortation to obedience with promiſes of bleſſing, and his dehortation from diſobedience with terrible threatnings, then <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. ſhuts up that diſcourſe after this manner, <hi>I call hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth to record this day againſt you, that I have ſet before you life and death, bleſſing and curſing; therefore chuſe life, that both thou and thy ſeed may live.</hi> In which remarkable words, according to Gods interpretation of them, which is alwayes according to truth, it is manifeſtly apparant, that they who chooſe the way of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, chooſe life; and ſo by the Law of Contraries, they who chooſe the way of Diſobedience chooſe death, which is a compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive word, including the fearful miſery of both worlds. It may <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1. 8. 1 Cor. 6. 9. 10. Epheſ. 5. 7. 1 John 3. 5.</note>be truly ſaid to all ignorant perſons, covetous muckworm's diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſinners, and every other perſon abiding in their unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate eſtate; You are in love with everlaſting burnings: you long to be in the lake which burns with fire and brimſtone, which ſhall never be quenched, becauſe they walk in thoſe ways and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that eſtate, which infallibly brings to that miſery. As we ſay to perſons that feed on ſuch meates as are unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and dangerous, you long to be ſick, and be in your grave: becauſe they will not forbear what will make them ſick, &amp; bring them to the houſe of rotteneſs: And God himſelfe, whoſe language will not be reformed by any deluded ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vain philoſophy, ſpeakes after the ſame rate, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. 36. <hi>He that ſinnes againſt me, wrongeth his owne ſoul, all they that hate me,</hi> as all do, who do not make the choice I have been ſpeaking of, <hi>love Death;</hi> And if ſo, how can it be with reaſon expected, that God, Angels, or men ſhould pitty them under it! I remember what God by <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Lean not to thine owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> and <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 12. <hi>Seest thou a man wiſe in his own conceit! there is more hope of a fool then of him.</hi> Certainly, if wicked ones would ceaſe to be both Judges &amp; parties in their own caſe (which is the moſt fooliſh, and unreaſonable thing in the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for) they muſt be forced to acknowledge the choice I am pleading for, to be the beſt choice. Let this be put to the votes of Heaven, and earth, I had almoſt ſaid, and of hell alſo, to conſider what choice is beſt, and it will be clearly carried for the godli's, againſt the wicked's choyce. To begin with the votes of heaven; God the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt (as you have heard) do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58289:35"/>
all men to make, and commend, and reward them moſt highly for making the holy choice. The innumerable company of holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels manifeſt their approbation of it by rejoycing when any perſon <note place="margin">Luk. 15. 7.</note>truly repents, and thereby declaredly forſaketh his former choice, and ownes no choice, but that which <hi>Mary</hi> in the Text made. Hence it is uſually ſaid, the teares of the penitent are the wine of Angels, that is, they are much refreſhed to obſerve them. And for all the glorified Spirits, which are before Gods holy throne <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 10. Heb. 12. 14. Rev. 21. 27.</note>in heaven, they had never been admitted into that blisful place, if they had not choſen the holy path which leads to it. Let us now come down to gather the Votes of the earth; Let holy <hi>David</hi> (as ſuch) ſpeak for himſelf, and conſequently the ſenſe of all holy ones, <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 119. 30 <hi>I have choſen the way of truth,</hi> and verſ. 173. <hi>I have choſen thy precepts;</hi> But then let us conſider whether any thing of this nature may be expected from the wicked. Certainly at ſome times when under great outward afflictions, inward awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Conſcience, and under the ſentence of death in their own apprehenſions, ſome of them wil ſpeak more holy truths in an hour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then they have done in ſeven years before, they abound with good diſcourſes, as if they had newly dropt down from heaven; They ſpeak truly and eloquently of the vanity of the creatures, of the woful effects of ſin; the unvaluable comfort of a pardon in the bloud of Chriſt, call upon all that are about them, not to follow their former wicked examples, but to be ſure to chooſe the ways of God, and the company of his people, which, if God ſpare them, and dare believe them, they will not ſtick to make him large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes before many witneſſes of better behaviour towards him all the remaining part of their days. So that in this caſe we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal not onely from the wicked to the Godly, but from the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to themſelves, from them, when their Conſciences are aſleep, to the ſame perſons, when their Conſciences are awakned.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, what charity is it, to account thoſe wicked, whoſe expreſſions are ſo pious? I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. God forbid that I, who need ſo much charity my ſelf, ſhould be uncharitable to others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some, yea many that have ſpoken ſo (as common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proveth) have afterwards, being reprieved from death, for a while returned to ſuch manifeſt wickedneſſe, as is inconſiſtent with the power of godlineſſe. Unleſſe, (which the Scripture will not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58289:36"/>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 10, 11.</note> bear, although this hypocritical age will) men ſhould ſay, O ye h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly drunkards, religious fornicators, godly ſwearers, pious cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Kingdom of heaven ſtands open to receive you. All of the better ſort on earth always vote for the choice of the Text; and ſome of the worſt of men and women at ſome times: But ſure no good Votes can be found in ſo bad a place as hell. I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuggeſt at preſent the ſpeech of the rich man the parable ſpeaks of, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 28. who when in hell, deſired that his five brethren might be warned not to come to that place of torment which they could not avoid, unleſſe they made a better choice then himſelf had done, and no choice could be effectual to that end, but the choice in the Text. I enquire not into the motive of that warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I am ſure the matter was unqueſtionably right. Oh that theſe conſiderations may be duly weighed by the children of men, before it be too late. I dare adde no more to preſſe the firſt branch of the Exhortation, and am much troubled, that I can now ſpeak ſo little to the ſecond branch, which alſo deſerves a moſt vigorous enforcement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Branch</hi> 2. To preſſe you who hear me this day, to make the choice in the Text early; Give me leave to offer ſome few quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Conſiderations, which I muſt do little more then name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 1. We are by the indiſpenſible command of God to make this choice early <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth.</hi> Now ſaith the Text, tis not left as a matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and at our own liberty, when we will begin to make this choice, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 33. Chriſt calls upon the children of men to <hi>ſeek firſt the kingdom of heaven and the righteouſneſſe thereof,</hi> which is as much in effect, as if he had ſaid; If you dare follow the advice of me, who am a wonderful Counſellor, let the firſt, and unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable choice be fixed upon God and the things of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 2. Tis the moſt reaſonable thing in the world that it ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe (as we have ſhewed largely) God, and the things of his Kingdome do beſt, and indeed onely deſerve our early choice, and nothing is more reaſonable then to be guided in our choice, by the different worth of Objects that are before us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Wiſdom is the principal thing, therefore get wiſdom, and with all thy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58289:36"/>
gettings get underſtanding.</hi> That which is principal, muſt be firſt and moſt regarded, what ever be neglected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The earlier this choice is made, the eaſier will our work be to get and keep out of forbidden pathes.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly let men begin never ſo ſoon to leave the ways of ſin, and to walk in the ways of God they will find it ſufficiently diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to turn their back upon wicked company, and to give a bill of divorce to their moſt beloved ſins: But the longer they have been in league with ſinners, and the longer they have been wedded to any ſinful courſe, the difficulty will certainly increaſe by thoſe means. The Prophet ſpeaks fully to this point, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 23. <hi>Can the Ethiopian change his skin? or the Leopard his ſpots? then may ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo do good who are accuſtomed to do evil.</hi> The <hi>Ethiopian</hi> cannot change his skin, nor the Leopard his ſpots; So that the Prophet hints it as impoſſible: And therefore I may well aſſert it as very difficult for an accuſtomed ſinner to return to God; and without more then ordinary grace, it would remain everlaſtingly impoſſible for ſuch an one to be brought over to the obedience of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 3. A late choice will certainly be very prejudicial to us in this, if not alſo in the other world. The broken bones that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny get in their younger days, before they be ſober and wiſe in the government of themſelves, although they may be ſet again, yet they have many painful remembrances of them afterwards. Tis ſo proportionably in ſpiritual matters. Mens dodging with God, and delaying to work his work may coſt them much dearer then they are aware. God made his beloved <hi>Job</hi> in bitterneſſe to poſſeſſe the ſins of his youth, <hi>Job</hi> 13. 26. Although they who make this right choice late, ſhal not wholly looſe the happineſſe of the other world, yet they, who early chooſe the ways of God, are ordinarily ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner under the light of Gods reconciled countenance, which is, as it were, an Heaven upon earth: And if that be ſuppoſed as true (which goes currant with many learned and ſober Divines, which I cannot now diſcuſſe) that there are degrees of glory in heaven, they who engage late in Gods vineyard, will throughout eternity poſſeſſe Heavens glory in a leſſe degree, then otherwiſe they might have been capable of; So that on ſuch a ſuppoſition late commers unto God, ſeem in ſome reſpects, by their delaies to ſuffer eternal prejudice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58289:37"/>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 4. Gods eminent acceptation of early comers into his waies, ought to be of ſpecial force to engage us to follow the counſel of this Exhortation. 'Tis our duty to ſtudy how we may do that which is acceptable in the ſight of God; and not only ſo, but likewiſe to labour with all our might after that which is moſt acceptable to God. Now Gods remarkable acceptation of thoſe <note place="margin">Coloſ 3. 20.</note>who early chooſe him, and his precious waies, is reſtified by the high commendations he in his Word beſtows upon them. This ſtands on Record for the praiſe of young <hi>Timothy</hi> as long as the bleſſed Book of God ſhall be found in the hands of any perſon, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note>
               <hi>That from a child he had known the Scriptures, which were able to make him wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi> 'Tis greater honour, and ſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Gods holy ones, to be a ſervant of Chriſt, then Emperour of the world. But to be as <hi>Mnaſon</hi> was, an old diſciple, one <note place="margin">Acts 21. 15.</note>who choſe Chriſts ſervice early, and ſo for a long time had been in Chriſts Family; doth unqueſtionably bring a further degree of honour, and upon that account he is recorded in ſacred Story. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 5. <hi>Salute my well-beloved</hi> Epenetus, <hi>who is the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits of</hi> Achaia <hi>unto Chriſt.</hi> Gods ſoul hath deſired ſuch firſt ripe fruits. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7. 1. And therefore this is ſpoken of as a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular commendation. Such Primroſes are a delightful ſight in Gods Garden. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 7. <hi>Salute</hi> Andronicus, <hi>and</hi> Junia, <hi>my Kinſmen, and my fellow-priſoners, who are of note among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who alſo were in Chriſt before me.</hi> Theſe laſt words are very obſervable. This glorious Apoſtle ſeems to prefer thoſe private Chriſtians above himſelf, becauſe of their early choice. True Chriſtianity makes any man noble, early Chriſtianity more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 5. 'Tis a moſt baſe and disingenuous thing to make this choice late. In the time of the Law, the firſt and the choiceſt of perſons and things, were ſet apart for God, and the beſt and worſt were worthily rejected by him. With what face almoſt can any ſinner come before God, to offer his late ſervice to him! How eaſily may God make him like the man without the wedding garment ſpeechleſſe before him! God may ſay to ſuch an one, Satan, the world, and the fleſh, have had the ſervice of your firſt and beſt daies, let them for me take the worſt alſo. Muſt your God have the worlds and the devils leavings, or nothing! I abhor the motion. God needs not our beſt ſervices, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58289:37"/>
much better ſervice then we are able with our beſt abilities of ſoul and body to afford him; And therefore to offer him the laſt and worſt of our ſervices, muſt needs be highly provoking. This is clear from thoſe words of the Prophet, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>If ye offer the blood for Sacrifice, is it not evil? Offer it now unto thy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, will he be pleaſed with thee, or accept thy perſon, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts?</hi> The Interrogation is to be reſolved into this Negation, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> He will not accept thy perſon, when thou bringeſt a blind or lame ſacrifice: and can it be reaſonably imagined, that the great and glorious God ſhould accept of ſuch ſorry things, as a ſilly mortal man would juſtly ſcorn; Oh friends, this baſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuity hath coſt many of Gods people very dear. Although all that rightly chooſe God, and his waies, at what time ſoever, are accepted with him, and beloved by him; yet it is well enough conſiſtent with his love, guided by an infinite Wiſdome, not to manifeſt the ſame to ſuch provokers of a long time. How many have we known (ſome of whichwere undoubtedly Gods dear ones) who have gone many years together roaring to the very borders of the Grave, and no comfort could be faſtned upon them by the moſt skilful <hi>Barnabaſſes;</hi> and this the great Spring of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting fear, they ſtrongly apprehend, it is too late, it is too late: If they had come in ſooner, they might have found acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance, but they think that God will diſdain to accept of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils orts; and therefore the door of hope ſeems to be ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And certainly Satan, who needs no help of any to make Arguments for him to diſpute againſt the trembling Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians hope in God, when he finds ſo many terrible things delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Scripture againſt this common ſin of delaying to turn to God, he will be ready to improve them to the utmoſt. For the awakening of the ſecure, I will mention a place or two to this purpoſe. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14. We have theſe words of God, that roar like thunder in the ears of Procraſtinators. <hi>Curſed be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, who hath in his flock a male, and voweth, and ſacrificeth to the Lord a corrupt thing; for I am a great King, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and my Name is dreadful among the Heathen.</hi> The male of the flock is judged the beſt of the flock; and therefore God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth his curſe upon thoſe, who put him off with worſe: No hope then appears of Gods acceptance of our worſt, of our late, lame, and blind ſacrifices. The other place is that of the Pſalmiſt,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58289:38"/>
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 95. 7. God calls upon men preſently without ſo much as one day's delay to turn to him; and that Exhortation is preſſed in the following Verſes, by an Argument taken from the woful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of thoſe that delayed, and put off God from year to year, till he would no longer bear it, <hi>v.</hi> 10. for in <hi>v.</hi> 11. God tels him his mind in ſuch terrible language, that their ears might well tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and their hearts tremble at the receiving of it: <hi>Unto whom I ſware in my wrath, that they ſhould not enter into my reſt.</hi> I do not remember any ſuch terrible Text in all the Bible againſt Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, Blaſphemers, who are incarnate devils, or any ſort of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that can be named. God threatneth to damn all ſorts of Chriſtleſſe ſinners; but he doth not manifeſt ſo much fury, as to ſwear, they ſhall not partake of his mercy: So that Satan hath this dreadful advantage againſt thoſe, who have unworthily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed to turn to God, if they afterwards begin to lament after God: Satan will be ready to entertain them with ſuch ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions as theſe, as good nothing, as nothing to the purpoſe; there is no hope for them, they ſhould have come ſooner, and if they will not believe him, he bids them take their Bible, and read in the 95. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> where againſt thoſe that have provoked God by delaies, he ſwears, they ſhould never enter into his reſt. Thus I have diſpatched five Conſiderations to provoke you to a ſpeedy choice of the good part which ſhall never be taken from you.</p>
            <p>I dare add no more, becauſe I muſt needs ſpend the remaining part of the time in ſpeaking concerning the ſad Providence which hath brought us together at this time. And becauſe it is not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all with me upon ſuch occaſions to make any large diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the dead, (the main ſcope of Funeral Sermons being the inſtruction of the living, and not the commendation of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed) I ſhall in my following work confine my meditations to theſe two general heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall give an account briefly, why I now vary from my ordinary courſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall deliver what I judge meet for your edification, ſo far as the ſtraits of time will permit me.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If any demand, why I now undertake to ſpeak of the dead (being beſides my ordinary practice,) My Anſwer is ready; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I do not remember that ever I could with ſo much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58289:38"/>
and to ſo good purpoſe, ſpeak of any perſon, as I can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this excellent Gentlewoman, the ſolemnization of whoſe Funeral hath occaſioned this great Aſſembly: Particularly there are three reaſons, which ſatisfie my ſelf, and I doubt not but they will likewiſe ſatisfie any other perſon, who are worthy of, and willing to receive ſatisfaction concerning this matter: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Leſt by my ſilence, I ſhould deprive very many of a more then ordinary pattern for their holy imitation. Her converſation which lay open to publick view was very conſiderable: but there were many remarkable things in the more retired part of her life which were not commonly known; and yet the knowledge of them might be of ſingular uſe to direct and quicken many to like profitable exerciſes of piety: This copy of her life was freer from blots then the lives of many other worthy women.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A diſcourſe of this nature may be of uſe for the comfort of her near Relations; although the more evidences of her remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able piety are brought to their remembrances, the greatneſſe of their own loſſe is thereby the more clearly diſcovered. Yet ſuch ſelf-love as makes them confine their thoughts wholly to their own loſſe, neglecting the needful meditation of her incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gain, is certainly liable to reproof. Many that follow their graceleſſe Relations to the Grave (which did greatly love them, and were dearly beloved by them) are greatly dejected, chiefly upon this ground, becauſe of their great fears touching their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtate. But I can with confidence beſpeak the friends of this deceaſed Gentlewoman in like words to thoſe of our dear Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> Weep not for her, from <note place="margin">Luke 23. 28.</note>whoſe eyes all tears are wiped, but weep for your ſelves; weep for your ſurviving Chriſtleſſe Relations, and over the afflicted daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the more of theſe tears the better.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If I ſhould forbear to ſpeak concerning the holy life of this our deceaſed Chriſtian friend, how is it poſſible that the great duty of duly laying to heart this ſad viſitation we are now under, ſhould be performed by many of you! Who can be ſadly affected proportionably to a great loſſe, when for want of information, the loſſe is only apprehended as ordinary! Now God takes it very ill at their hands, who live careleſly under ſuch ſad Providences. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 57. 11. <hi>The righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58289:39"/>
that the righteous are taken away from the evil to come.</hi> A great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny think their whole duty is performed, if for two or three days after the hearing of ſuch news, their table talk be to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; Such a good Gentlewoman is dead, ſhe did much good in her place, I am ſorry for it: When it may be in a fortnight, or moneth after, 'tis almoſt utterly forgotten, that there was any ſuch perſon. The Scripture laſt mentioned tels you, That God many times ſnatcheth away his people by death, when ſome great evils are approaching to the places where they lived. I love not to conceive, or utter doleful prophecies, but my earneſt prayer to God is, that we may all walk penitently under this ſtroak, that greater diſpleaſure then we are at preſent aware of do not flow in upon us through this very great breach.</p>
            <p>I now addreſſe my ſelf to the laſt general head, I propounded to ſpeak to, <hi>viz.</hi> A brief account of ſome things, and but ſome things (for haſte) which were remarkable in the holy life of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Anne Petter.</hi> And here I might ſpeak of her in a threefold capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. 1. Natural. 2. Civil. 3. Spiritual. But I call to mind the rule obſerved by <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, in the praiſe of <hi>Gordius</hi> the Martyr: It is (ſaid he, or to this purpoſe) the vain-glorious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the world, when they would praiſe any perſon, to ſpeak of his Family, to derive his pedigree through many diſcents, to enlarge upon his natural diſpoſition, parts, education, learning, and ſuch other accompliſhments. <hi>Sed Eccleſia haec tanquam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervacua dimittit.</hi> The Church looks only at thoſe things which may glorifie Chriſt in his Saints, and thereby do good to them that remain alive. According to this rule, I ſhall forbear to ſpeak of her very loving, humble, and ingenuous temper. 2. Of the Family whereof ſhe was a Branch, although in it ſelf very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable according to the worlds account. Theſe were not the things ſhe did, or had cauſe over-much to value. My Diſcourſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concerning her, will be wholly confined to her ſpiritual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, and operations; for in reckoning up the eſtate of rich perſons, ſmall matters are not mentioned, their eſtates are not reckoned by pence, or ſhillings, but by pounds, by hundreds and thouſands: we ſhall do proportionably in this undertaking. And here alſo, ſhe might be conſidered perſonally, and relatively: but I ſhall not ſtand upon any curioſity of this nature. What I ſhall mention as obſervable in her, and very worthy of imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58289:39"/>
fals under theſe two general heads:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Her diſpoſition, and behaviour towards thoſe on Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Her affection, and carriage more immediately relating to the God of Heaven, and the things of Heaven.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, her diſpoſition, and behaviour towards them on Earth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. She was one of a publick, and conſequently of a very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſpirit. This ſhe manifeſted many waies, by her being conſtant, and fervent in her prayers for the publick welfare, by her ſadneſs, when at any time it fared ill with any part of the Church of Chriſt, although in Forain parts, where no preſent danger of any of her perſonal worldly concernments did biaſs her, by her great joy, when ſhe heard of its flouriſhing eſtate; And whereas a great many at their meeting with others enquire after news, that it may only furniſh them with matter for table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcourſe, and preſent them with variety of objects for their proud cenſures; her queſtions tending that way were uſually, if not conſtantly, expreſſed in this ſhort pious form, How doth it go abroad with the Church, and Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt? That was all in all to her, as to matter of news. It would be over-tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to go through all the inſtances, which might be mentioned on this account. I ſhall only touch upon one or two more; ſhe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced her publick ſpirit by the great and cordial reſpects, which upon all occaſions ſhe expreſſed towards thoſe that appeared gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly, and couragiouſly in the Cauſe of Chriſt. She would name them with honour, while living, and bitterly bewail their deaths, when taken hence by Gods angry hand. She could ſay with <hi>Deborah,</hi> Judg. 5. 9. <hi>My heart is towards the Governours of Iſrael, that offered themſelves willingly among the people. Bleſſe ye the Lord;</hi> And yet further, ſhe did not ſatisfie her ſelf by ſerving God with that which coſt her nought, ſhe never repined at any expence of money in the Cauſe of Chriſt. And which was much more conſiderable, having an only ſon left her, who was moſt dearly beloved by her, ſhe willingly parted with him for the ſervice of the publick intereſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She was very bountiful to thoſe that were in need, as many of you here preſent can teſtifie, from large and long experience: her charity was not hypocritical, like theirs ſpoken of, <hi>James</hi> 2. 15, 16. <hi>If a brother, or ſiſter be naked, and deſtitute of daily food,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58289:40"/>
and one of you ſay to them, Depart in peace, be you warmed and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; notwithſtanding you give them not thoſe things which are needful to the body, what doth it profit!</hi> One little handful were much better, then many ſuch mouth-fuls. Her charity was conſtant; ſhe did not content her ſelf once in a year to drop a ſmall alms, and then all the year after live like an hard-hearted, and cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſted Mammoniſt. She was daily begging, and receiving ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual alms from Heaven, and expreſſed her thankfulneſs to God for it, by giving out freely and frequently, for the ſupply of thoſe who were in want. Very many here, and elſewhere, might have deſervedly prayed for her, when living, uſing ſuch words as <hi>Paul</hi> for <hi>Oneſiphorus.</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 16. The Lord give mercy to the houſe of Miſtreſs <hi>Petter,</hi> for ſhe often refreſhed me and mine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Her unfeigned &amp; fervent love to thoſe of the houſhold of Faith, <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note>was very manifeſt; partly, 1. By her bountiful gifts beſtowed on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ſhe was not (as many are) affraid to ſee, or hear of ſuch objects, but as the Prophet ſpeaketh, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 32. 8. <hi>The liberal perſon deviſeth liberal things,</hi> and ſo did ſhe; if at any time ſhe by information offered by others, or enquiry made by her ſelf, came to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any godly perſon in diſtreſs, ſhe opened her purſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any motives, beſides what her own inflamed heart furniſhed her with, and ſent liberal tokens to thoſe whoſe faces ſhe never did, or ſhall ſee, till ſhe behold them in the Kingdome of Glory. 2. And by admitting them before others into familiar ſociety with her ſelf, although never ſo mean in the world; herein very like the man after Gods own heart, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 16. 2. <hi>O my ſoul, thou haſt ſaid unto the Lord, Thou art my Lord, my goodneſſe extendeth not to thee, but to the Saints that are in the Earth, and to the excellent, in whom is all my delight.</hi> She would be almoſt frighted, when ſhe ſaw any come within her doors, that ſhe knew could not ſpeak, and were unwilling to hear of the things of God, but a poor Chriſtian was a very acceptable gueſt to her at any time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. She was one of a vey peaceable temper, and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 9. Rom. 12. 19.</note>worthy to be called a Child of God. If money would purchaſe it, ſhe was content, nay, very glad to buy it with the loſs of right; ſhe was in this reſpect eminently God-like, that when others have been manifeſtly guilty of the breach of peace,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58289:40"/>
and had not humility enough to offer reconciliation, ſhe was willing to be the firſt in ſeeking reconciliation. And when argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with men prevailed not, ſhe wept in ſecret, and poured forth prayers before God to obtain it, and rejoyced wonderfully <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 18, 19</note>in the good ſucceſs of any means that could be uſed to procure and preſerve it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. She was one of a healing ſpirit, which appears by her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, wherein ſhe was very careful to avoid names of diviſion, and declared the great grief of her ſoul for the unhappy differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among Gods precious people: and if any ſpake to her of any that differed from her in judgement, as if they wondred, how ſhe could be familiar with them, ſhe would ordinarily make this Anſwer, I am verily perſwaded they truly fear God, and ſo long I can heartily cloſe with them, and (over-looking what I conceive to be their infirmities) honour them for the image of Jeſus Chriſt that ſhines in them. Poor divided <hi>England</hi> hath great cauſe bitterly to lament the loſs of ſuch a Chriſtian, who excelled in this kind: Alſo like Chriſt, ſhe was much in prayer for this needful union, <hi>John</hi> 17. 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. She was exceeding careful of the ſouls of thoſe that were under her charge; which was evidenced by the great pains ſhe took to inſtruct them: beſides her holy example before them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and daily prayers for them, ſhe was wont to hear her ſervants repeat over their Catechiſmes once a week, eſpecially before their receiving the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; Oh that her example herein might provoke others to greater care, as to the ſouls of their ſervants. They might conſider, that God might have made them ſervants: but ſeeing God hath been ſo indulgent towards them, and hath provided for their eaſe, by giving them eſtates, ſo that they can keep ſervants; it would be but an equal and ingenuous diſcovery of their thankfulneſs to God for that mercy, by taking care that their ſervants might find ſome time to do Gods work, as well as their work. And indeed who ever came near her to receive corporal alms, ſhe could not ſend them away empty, if fit objects of charity; and her alms was uſually double for the ſoul as well as the body. She would call upon elder perſons to attend upon the publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and to bring up their children to read; and the children ſhe would exhort to dutifulneſs to their parents, diligence in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58289:41"/>
their work, and care to learn their Catechiſmes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to her affection, and carriage towards God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. She was one that evidenced abundance of love to Jeſus Chriſt. She was not like thoſe mentioned, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 31. who profeſs much love with their lips, but little or no evidence of it in their lives, whereby their hearts are diſcovered. <hi>John</hi> 14. 21. <hi>He that hath his Commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth him:</hi> Now as to the Evangelical keeping of Gods Commandments, 'tis very rare to meet with any that was ſo willingly, and chearfully induſtrious at all times to comply with them in a holy conformity, as ſhe was. She was ſo far from ſcanting God in point of manifeſt duty, that ſometimes ſhe was ready in ſome caſes not ſo manifeſt, to over-do; and out of the abundance of her heart, would her mouth ſpeak often, and much of the precious love of Jeſus Chriſt. She was wont to ſay, that no divine argument did more deeply affect her, then that of the love of Chriſt. Before the manifeſtation of Chriſts love to her ſoul, ſhe was to admiration importunate for the obtaining of it, and afterwards as careful to preſerve it, as the Church in <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>She held him, and was not willing for ſo much as one day or hour to let him go.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. She was very zealous in the worſhip of God in private, as well as in publick: She was daily exerciſed (if health permitted) in the reading of the holy Scriptures; and for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther read over the whole Bible once in each year. Beſides alſo ſhe read much in the approved Treatiſes of our moſt eminent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Divines; by which means ſhe attained to a very great meaſure of knowledge, and was very ſound in the faith. I could not obſerve in more then twelve years acquaintance with her, that ſhe was in the leaſt infected with any one of the errours of the times. Oh that in theſe exerciſes which are ſo profitable, many, eſpecially of her rank, would follow her, as their pattern. It would make any holy ſoul to mourn bitterly in ſecret, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how many Gentlewomen can talk even to admiration, of all ordinary worldly ſubjects; but if any diſcourſe of the points of Religion be begun in their hearing, they are put quite out of their element, and cannot hold pace in ſuch diſcourſes one half quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour, then many of them can ſay no more, but yea, or
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58289:41"/>
nay, becauſe they underſtand not perfectly what is ſaid, and are aſhamed to diſcover their ignorance by a total ſilence, or by contradiction, when they want arguments to maintain their diſſent: If they would wiſely redeem ſome time from their ſleep, and many hours from that time that is uſually beſtowed in an abhorred prodigality, in the over-curious decking, and trimming their vile bodies, and if further they would beware of trifling away ſo many after-noons in dangerous viſits of all ſorts of perſons, of their rank, although apparent enemies of Jeſus Chriſt, they might gain much time for theſe and all other holy exerciſes. I am ſure Chriſt is little beholding to them, who are ſo tender of their own reputation, that to avoid that which the fooliſh world calls incivility, they will make bold to rob him of abundance of precious hours, which his ſervice cals for, and deſerves at their hands; and ſure none are in this true friends to their ſouls intereſt; but if any godly perſons ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend by their over-familiar converſe with Chriſts enemies, it may, and doth juſtly provoke him to turn former familiarity with them into long and very ſad eſtrangements, for which they may thank their own unwarrantable civilities as they ſtile them; Some there are, who content themſelves in reading ſome part of the Scripture, when they have nothing elſe to do; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this be a chief part, yet certainly not the whole of their duty; for it is not the bare reading of the Scriptures that will make them Chriſtians, but the underſtanding of them; and for this end, what means more proper, and probable, then the peruſal of the Treatiſes of the godly Learned, who excel in the gift of ſound interpretation of the Scriptures. I have many times thought that the devil is willing, and it is for his intereſt, that ſome ſhould read the Scriptures, if they be not forward to uſe other helps for the underſtanding of them: Becauſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures being barely read, and not underſtood, doth quiet ſome of their working Conſciences, and yet by this means alone many of them are not at all directed, and quickned in thoſe exerciſes, wherein the main power of Godlineſs doth conſiſt. Surely it will be very confounding in the great day of Accounts to thoſe rich perſons, who have neglected theſe duties, when it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that many a poor Chriſtian that was forced to riſe early, and go to bed late, to get barley bread to keep themſelves, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58289:42"/>
from ſtarving, have yet ſpent more hours in reading the Scriptures, hearing weekly Lectures, peruſing the Treatiſes of godly Divines in one year, then they have done in ſeven, happily in twenty years, or all the time of their life. But I ſee my deep ſenſe of the woful neglect of theſe neceſſary duties hath tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me ſtrangely, and made me much larger upon this Head then I intended. I will recompence this prolixity with all conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent brevity upon the next Head, which yet deſerves as large a Diſcourſe; and that is</p>
            <p n="3">3. Her moſt remarkable conſtancy in the duty of private pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in the ſeaſons of it. When ſhe was at home, and her fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-occaſions extraordinary by reaſon of gueſts, it would not cauſe her to omit, or ſhorten that neceſſary ſervice; when abroad, and tired with travel, (which many would take for a compleat excuſe) ſhe would not betake her ſelf to her bed, till this duty was duly diſpatched. 'Tis a very ſad thing to conſider, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who call themſelves Chriſtians, and are angry if others do not ſubſcribe to their judgement of themſelves, without giving the leaſt hint of backwardneſs, who yet ſeldome, if at any time pour out their requeſts before God in ſecret. Alas ſuch perſons conſider not that a wretch newly crept out of one Gaol, and groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for by another, may yet in a crowd go along with a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a great Prince, when it is preſented in the name of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but for any Subject to have leave, and heart to go privately upon all occaſions into the Prince his preſence, with Petitions, argues an high degree of familiarity. And as ſhe was much in begging mercy, ſo likewiſe in thankfulneſs for mercies vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to her ſelf, or any of hers; ſhe uſed to ſpeak much of them, and once in every year to ſet a day apart for the exerciſe of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to God for them, by which ſhe evidenced her ſelf to be a moſt wiſe, and ingenuous Chriſtian. You have now heard ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of her zeal in the private worſhip of God, and it cannot be reaſonably conceived, that ſhe was leſs careful of Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſervice. Many that ſeem forward for that, are wholly negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of private worſhip, but it would be very ſtrange to obſerve the contrary. Hypocriſie (the Epidemical diſeaſe) will leave no ſtage-work undone.</p>
            <p>Now here I might inſiſt largly on her dilligence in attending upon the preaching of the Word, when ſhe had ſtrength of body,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58289:42"/>
and was conveniently ſeated. She uſed (to prevent drouſineſſe and diſtraction) to ſtand, fixing her eye upon the Preacher; <note place="margin">Luke 4. 28.</note>which ſhe was wont to ſay, ſhe learned of (the Elect Lady) her Religious mother. And when ſhe was to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, her care to come a prepared gueſt to that bleſſed feaſt, was more then ordinary: Much time was ſpent in the hard, but gainful duty, of ſelf-examination, and importunate prayer, that Chriſt would prepare her for, and bid her welcome to that holy Banquet. And indeed her great zeal to the worſhip of <note place="margin">Eſa. 58. 13.</note>God appeared clearly in her ſingular delight in that time, which by Gods appointment is ſet apart for ſpecial attendance upon it, I mean the holy Sabbath of God: Many (Oh that I were not forced to ſay, moſt) keep onely ſuch a Sabbath, as Divines uſe fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to call, the Sabbath of aſſes; when they have tyred themſelves in the week day, in the worlds drugery, when the Lords day comes, they riſe later in the morning of that day, and go to bed more early in the evening of it, then at other times; By which meanes their own (as the bodies of their beaſts) have much eaſe and refreſhment, but as for ſpending the whole time of it (the moſt equal thing in the world upon many unanſwerable grounds) in the publick, and private exerciſes of Gods worſhip, this they can by no means brook: But as for this excellent Gentlewoman, as ſhe had a better heart towards God, ſo was her behaviour out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly anſwerable. She uſed to riſe more early upon the Lords <note place="margin">Amos 8. 5.</note>day, then upon any other day, no weather hindred her from the publick Aſſembly, and what time was not ſpent in publick, was exactly imployed in private duties of Gods appointment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. She was one of a very Humble Spirit, which appeared in her affability, and courteſie to the meaneſt perſons who had occaſion to make uſe of her; And when ſhe ſpake (as ſhe did often) of the merciful Providences of God towards her, in providing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably for her all her days, as to the concernments of both worlds, ſhe would ever expreſſe her admiration of Gods great goodneſſe towards her, by acknowledging that what God had done graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <note place="margin">Luke 1. 48. Jud. 6. 15. 1 Pet. 5. 5.</note>for her, was for one, who (in her own thoughts) was the meaneſt of her fathers family. I ſcarce have known any more adorned with the glorious robe of humility then ſhe was.</p>
            <p n="4">4. She was a chearful not a ſullen Chriſtian; by her chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Gods precious ways, ſhe did more credit the Goſpel of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58289:43"/>
Chriſt, in one year, then many other drooping and lowring Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in a long time. She was none of Gods whinnels, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every petty outward affliction, or becauſe inward comforts were not diſpenced at that time, and in that meaſure they expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, like froward children, are ready to throw away what is in their hands already; her great care was to get a clean and quiet conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and when the Bird in the boſom did ſing ſweetly, ſhe could well enough digeſt many other diſappointments.</p>
            <p n="5">5. She was very patient under affliction and living to ſo great an age as ſhe did, it cannot be imagined but that ſhe ſhared in the <note place="margin">Act. 14. 22.</note>common lot of Chriſtians. She had much of that ingenuity which was in holy <hi>Job,</hi> which ſhe diſcovered by thoſe words, <hi>Shall we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 2. 10.</note>
               <hi>receive good at the hands of God, and not evil?</hi> When her paines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in the time of her ſickneſſe, towards her end, ſhe would ſay, I love God ſtill, I will truſt him ſtill; And in the greateſt afflictions that ſhe was at any time under, ſhe was ſo far from fainting, and diſcontent, that ſhe would ſay, We muſt not be overmuch troubled for worldly loſſes, or croſſes, theſe are but chips of the croſſe, we deſerve that God ſhould make our burden more heavy to all eternity.</p>
            <p n="6">6. She was a moſt heavenly minded Chriſtian, She abounded <note place="margin">Col. 3. 1. 2.</note>alwayes in diſcourſes tending that way (not onely in her ſickneſſe) but all the time of her health; and could ſcarce be patient to hear any long diſcourſes of other ſubjects, when in the company of Gods people, who could ſpeak to better purpoſe. And when any of her Relations came to viſit her, before their parting, ſhe would uſually ſay; Nothing troubled her more, then to think, that while they had been together, they had done one another ſo little good, and been ſo little helpful to each other in the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 16. Rom. 4. 20. 1 Tim. 4. 8.</note> 7. To name no more, She was eminent in the eminent Grace of Faith. She gave the Lord much glory by believing. Her Faith appeared to be of the right ſtamp, becauſe it cloſed with, and made improvement of all promiſes for this life, and for that which is to come. When any worldly difficulties we objected in referrence to her ſelf or near Relations, ſhe would ſay, God had never failed her <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 37.</note>yet, and he was all-ſufficient, and therefore ſhe would truſt God for all. Now that Faith which uſeth to feed upon former experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences is ordinarily ſtrong. And when any dangers were before
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58289:43"/>
her, ſhe was very couragious and undaunted; Which was the iſſue of her well grounded Faith. When the troubles were in <hi>Kent,</hi> and a great many men and women, were at their wits end, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly deſtitute of Faith, were ready to cry, and run from place to place, one being ſolicitous, where to diſpoſe of his money, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hide his perſon in ſafety, ſhe was quiet; She ſaid, it was not bolts and bars, that kept her in ſafety in quiet times, but Gods almighty Providence, and that was as able to ſecure her now, and therefore ſhe could then ſleep in peace, as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 3. 8. Nor was her faith leſſe obſervable in reference to its actings about the concernments of the other world. And here her faith of Adherence and Evidence (as it is uſually expreſſed) were both very ſtrong. Tis true, Satan was very buſie with her, to get her from the Caſtle of the Promiſes, where her ſtrength lay; but God had made her ſo wiſe a Chriſtian, as to have the Goſpel conſidered <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 23.</note>as the Law of Faith alwaies in her thoughts, and by that means ſhe was made afraid at any time of neglecting to caſt her ſelf whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the free grace of God in Chriſt for ſalvation, according to the Covenant. The Commands of God made her fearful of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the duty of Prayer, of miſpending her precious time, and other preſcribed duties; So likewiſe the clear commandment above mentioned, for believing, made her as much afraid to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 16.</note>that duty, which is the moſt eminent of all Chriſtian duties, and the moſt helpful to all the reſt.</p>
            <p>As to the faith of evidence, ſhe attained to ſuch a degree of it, that by it (which was a moſt incomparable priviledge) ſhe was lifted up ry much above the fear of death. Her language in the time of her ſickneſſe was, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly,</hi> and for my part, it was to my great admiration to hear of what ſhe ſpake frequently, and chearfully concerning many particulars relating to her funeral, not needful to be imparted. Now I have finiſhed what I intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Providence which brought us together at this time. And me thinks, I hear ſome of you to ſpeak after this manner; Why no more? To which I anſwer, All the flowers of a garden ſo well ſtored, as the garden of her long, and Chriſtian life was, with a grateful variety of ſweet and beautiful Graces, cannot in a ſhort time be gathered, and preſented in one handful. But a far greater number are more apt to ſay, Why ſo much of her virtues, and nothing of her infirmities? Was ſhe while living in this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58289:44"/>
world, perfect, of the Church Triumphant and not Militant? To which I anſwer, leaſt I ſhould ſeem to flatter, which none that know my temper will readily charge me with, it muſt be confeſſed, that ſhe had her infirmitie; (as all others, of the beſt of Saints have in this life) yet becauſe they are unqueſtionably covered, forgiven, and forgotten by Chriſt, it will argue us the more Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to forget them, as he hath given us an example. Beſides I obſerve in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. where the holy Ghoſt is enlarged in the praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the holy Patriarchs, and other Worthies, who had (at leaſt ſome of them) greater miſcarriages then I ever obſerved in her, that none of their praiſes are ſtained with any blots, or buts of their ſinful infirmities.</p>
            <p>To ſumme up all, this excellent Gentlewoman Mrs. <hi>A. Petter,</hi> ſo manifeſted her Graces in all Relations and Conditions, that it may be truly ſaid of her: She was a moſt loving, reſpectful, and obedient Wife, a very tender and careful Mother, a conſcionable and bountiful Miſtreſſe, a peaceable and helpful Neighbour: In Proſperity ſhe was very chearful, thankful, and fruitful; In Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity very ſubmiſſive, ſelf-ſearching, and penitent. Well, what now remaines, but that I beſpeak you all in the words of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 37. <hi>Go ye and do likewiſe:</hi> And then (craving pardon for my very unuſual prolixity) I ſhut up all with like words to thoſe of the bleſſed Apoſtle. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Conſider what hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58289:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
